…大家注意 暴风仍在向西移动
... and I'll tell you what, the storm system's still moving west.
在看什么呢 卡罗琳？
What are you looking at, Caroline?
看风 妈妈
The wind, Mom.
他们说飓风要来了
They say the hurricane is coming.
我感觉像在一艘船上
I'm on a boat.
漂浮着
I'm drifting.
我可以做什么吗 妈妈？
Can I do anything for you, Mom?
让你舒服点？
Make anything easier?
哦 宝贝…
Oh, sugar...
没什么可做的
There's nothing left to do.
就这样吧
Is what it is.
我越来越睁不开眼了
Finding it harder to keep my eyes open.
嘴里像是塞满了棉花
My mouth's full of cotton.
好了 好了 黛西女士
There, there, Miss Daisy.
你快把自己抓伤了
You gonna scratch yourself to ribbons.
药还要吗 妈妈？
Do you want any more medication, Mother?
医生说用多点没关系
Doctor said you could have as much as you want.
这样大家都不会遭罪
No need for anybody to suffer.
有个朋友说过 她甚至都没有机会
A friend told me that she never had the chance
跟她母亲道别
to say goodbye to her mother.
- 我想… - 没事
- I wanted to... - It's okay.
我想告诉你 我会非常想念你的…
I wanted to tell you how much I'm gonna miss you so...
妈妈
Mom.
哦 卡罗琳
Oh, Caroline.
你怕吗？
Are you afraid?
我很好奇
I'm curious.
接下来会怎样？
What comes next?
火车站建于1918年
They built the train station in 1918.
开站那天我父亲也去了
My father was there the day it opened.
他说那天还请了
He said they had
铜管乐队表演
a tuba band playing.
还请来了整个南方最好的钟表匠
They had the finest clockmaker in all of the South
建了那座雄伟的大钟
to build that glorious clock.
那人叫…
His name was...
盖图先生
Mr. Gateau.
蛋糕先生 （盖图/Gateau在法语中是蛋糕之意）
Mr. Cake.
他娶了伊文格琳县一个克里奥尔人
（位于美国路易斯安那州中西部的一个县） （克里奥尔人-美国路易斯安那州的法国人后裔）
He was married to a Creole of Evangeline Parish
后来他们生了个儿子
and they had a son.
盖图先生先天失明
Mr. Gateau was, from birth, absolutely blind.
他们的儿子长大后就参了军
When their son was old enough, he joined the army.
他们向上帝祈祷 保佑他平安
And they prayed God would keep him out of harm's way.
好几个月 他除了建那钟 什么都没做
For months, he did nothing but work on that clock.
然后有一天
One day,
他们收到一封信
a letter came.
那天晚上工作完后
And Mr. Gateau, done for the night,
盖图先生就独自去睡觉了
went up, alone, to bed.
然后他们的儿子回来了
And their son came home.
他们把他埋在家族墓地里
They buried him in the family plot,
等他们死后 一家就能团聚了
where he would be with them when their time came.
蛋糕先生继续建造那座钟
Mr. Cake worked on his clock,
耗尽心血 终于完工
laboring to finish.
那是一个值得纪念的早上
It was a morning to remember.
爸爸说 那天人山人海
Papa said there were people everywhere.
连泰迪・罗斯福都来了 （西奥多・罗斯福 昵称泰迪 美国第26任总统）
Even Teddy Roosevelt came.
钟倒走了！
It's running backwards!
我故意这么做的
I made it that way
这样那些在战争中死去的孩子们
so that perhaps the boys that we lost in the war
也许就会死而复生 回家来
might stand and come home again.
回家耕种
Home to farm,
工作
work,
生儿育女
have children.
过完他们漫长而充实的一生
To live long, full lives.
也许我自己的儿子也能回家来
Perhaps my own son might come home again.
如有得罪 请各位原谅
I'm sorry if I've offended anybody.
希望你们喜欢我的钟
I hope you enjoy my clock.
蛋糕先生自此再没出现过
Mr. Cake was never seen again.
有人说他心碎而死
Some say he died of a broken heart.
有人说他出海了
Some say he went to sea.
对不起
Excuse me.
我可以打个电话吗？我孩子请人照看着
Do you mind if I make a call? Somebody's watching my little boy.
当然
Sure.
希望我没让你失望
I hope I haven't disappointed you.
你不会让我失望的
You couldn't disappoint me.
我知道自己没什么才能
Well, I know I don't have much to show for myself.
把我的黑色手提箱找出来
Find my dark suitcase.
里面有本日记
There's a diary.
这个吗？
This?
能念给我听听吗？
Could you read it to me?
你就想这样？
Is this what you want to do?
我读过无数次了
I tried to read it a hundred different times.
妈妈 这并不是…
Mom, it's not exactly...
只是想听听你的声音 亲爱的
It's just the sound of your voice, darling.
好吧
Okay.
时间是1985年4月4日
It's dated April 4th, 1985.
上面写着新奥尔良
And it says New Orleans.
“这是我最后的遗言 也是遗嘱
"This is my last will and testament.
“我没留下什么 没财产 没钱 真的
"I don't have much to leave, few possessions, no money, really.
“我孤独地来 孤独地去 生不带来 死不带去
"I will go out of this world the same way I came in, alone and with nothing.
“我仅有的就是我的故事
"All I have is my story,
“我现在就写着 趁我还记得的时候
"and I'm writing it now while I still remember it.
“我的名字叫本杰明 本杰明・巴顿”
"My name is Benjamin. Benjamin Button."
我的出生很不寻常
And I was born under unusual circumstances.
那时一战刚结束
The First World War had ended,
后来我听说 我出生的那个夜晚特别好
and I've been told it was an especially good night to be born.
谢天谢地终于结束了！
Thank God it's over!
我们赢了！
We won the war!
世界大战结束了！
The Great War is over!
你来这干嘛？
What are you doing here?
托马斯
Thomas,
恐怕她快撑不住了
I'm afraid she's going to die.
什么？
What?
够了 你们都离她远点
That's enough. All of you, get away from her.
我已经尽快赶回来了 街上尽是人
I came as quickly as I could. The streets are filled with people.
托马斯
Thomas.
答应我 给他个容身之所
Promise me he has a place.
好的
Yeah.
她把生命给了我
She gave her life for me.
对此我毕生感激
And for that, I am forever grateful.
巴顿先生
Mr. Button.
托马斯！
Thomas!
托马斯
Thomas.
托马斯？你去哪？
Thomas? Where are you going?
嘿！你在这干嘛？
Hey! What are you doing there?
怀里的是什么？
What do you have there?
- 快点 奎尼 - 快 韦瑟斯先生！
- Come on, Queenie. - Now, Mr. Weathers!
得了 除了工作 我在这还有很多事要做
Come on, now, you know I ain't got nothing but work to do around here.
- 别 就一会 - 别犯傻了
- Come on. Just take some time. - Stop all this foolishness.
空气真清新
The air is sweet.
你今晚真迷人 奎尼小姐
You look very handsome tonight, Miss Queenie.
一如既往的美
Handsome as I've ever seen.
棕色真配你的眼睛
The brown matches your eyes.
哦 讨厌！
Oh, hush!
让我瞧瞧 你也不赖啊
Let's see here. You ain't no slouch yourself.
汉伯特回镇上了
Hambert's back in town.
他的两条腿没了 不过总算回来了
He came home legless, but he's home.
我知道你一度很迷恋他
I know you were sweet on him one time.
喜欢得都过头了
Sweeter than I should've been.
西蒙妮小姐又尿裤子了
Miss Simone messed herself.
哦 我的小祖宗
Oh, sweet Jesus.
她可别这样了 否则我要给她穿尿布了
She got to stop doing that or it's diapers for her.
- 我一会就去 詹姆森小姐！ - 快 奎尼 快来
- I'll be right there, Miss Jameson! - Now, Queenie, now come on.
好吧 奎尼马上过来
Okay, Queenie'll be right there.
外面太舒服了
It's awful nice out here.
出来透透气 别想那些事了
Come on out back for a moment. Take your mind off things.
你好坏
You're so bad.
- 上帝啊？ - 这是什么？
- What in God's name? - What's this?
哦 上帝保佑
Oh, the Lord done something here.
希望我没踩伤他
Hope I didn't hurt it none stepping on it like that.
我们最好交给警察处理
We best leave that for the police.
可怜的孩子
Poor baby.
我去找警察
I'll go.
肯定没人愿意收留他 来 宝贝
It's for sure nobody wanted to keep it. Come on, baby.
奎尼？你在哪 奎尼？
Queenie? Where are you, Queenie?
憋着！你去看下
Hold your water! You go deal with it.
好吧 不 你去 我马上就来
Okay. No, go, I'll be back.
奎尼 苹果她憋不住又尿了一身！
Queenie, Apple, she went and messed herself all over again!
简・查尔里斯 给她洗洗！
Jane Childress, start her a bath!
管好你自己的事 杜普雷太太
And mind your own business, Mrs. Duprey.
再没多久你也一团糟了
You'll be messing yourself soon enough.
有人偷了我的项链
Somebody stole my necklace.
好的 知道了 霍利斯特太太 我一会就来 好吗？
Okay. All right, Mrs. Hollister, I'll be right with you, okay?
回楼上去 听见了吗？
Go on back upstairs, hear?
你丑的像只旧罐子
You are as ugly as an old pot
可你仍是上帝的孩子
but you're still a child of God.
奎尼 你不在苹果她不肯洗澡！
Queenie, Apple, she won't take a bath without you!
饶了我吧
Mercy.
我马上就来！
I'll be right there!
好了 你就在这等我 好吗？
Okay. You just wait right here for me now, okay?
我姐姐给了我那条珍珠项链 我怎么也找不到
My sister gave me those pearls. I can't find them anywhere.
- 有人偷了我的珠宝 - 这这呢 霍利斯特夫人 看见了吗？
- Somebody's been stealing my jewelry. - They're right here, Mrs. Hollister. See?
就挂在你那雪白漂亮的脖子上 好了 都别吵了
Right around your pretty white neck. Now, come on. Hush all that noise.
- 罗斯医生还在这吗？ - 不知道
- Is Dr. Rose still here? - I don't know.
你的心脏很健康
Your heart is strong.
只要避免过度刺激
You just want to avoid any undue stimulation.
我相信各位女士会照看好他的？
I trust you ladies will help me out with that?
我有事找您 您能下楼来一趟吗？
I have something. Could you come downstairs?
从没见过 白内障导致几乎失明
Never seen anything like it. Nearly blind from cataracts.
我不确定他能不能听见 从骨骼看他有严重的关节炎
I'm not sure if he can hear. His bones indicate severe arthritis.
他的皮肤完全没有弹性 手脚都硬化了
His skin has lost all elasticity, and his hands and feet are ossified.
他的身体正在衰退 衰弱 一点都不像新生儿
He shows all the deterioration, the infirmities, not of a newborn,
更像是个80多岁行将踏进坟墓的老人
but of a man well in his 80s on his way to the grave.
他会死吗？
He's dying?
生活还没开始 他的身体就不行了
His body is failing him before his life's begun.
他从哪来？
Where'd he come from?
我姐姐的孩子 从拉斐特来（美国城市） 她遭遇了不幸
My sister's child. From Lafayette. She had an unfortunate adventure.
可怜的孩子 真是太不幸了 还是个白人
The poor child, he got the worst of it. Come out white.
有些地方专门收留这样的弃儿 奎尼
There are places for unwanted babies like these, Queenie.
这儿没地方再养一张嘴了
No room for another mouth to feed here.
尽管诺兰基金会出于好意
The Nolan Foundation, despite their good intentions,
可他们还是觉得这地方是个大麻烦
thinks this place is a large nuisance as it is.
- 一个孩子… - 你刚说他活不长
- A baby... - You said he don't have long.
奎尼 有些生物注定无法存活
Queenie, some creatures aren't meant to survive.
不 这个孩子 他是个奇迹 这是肯定的
No, this baby, he is a miracle. That's for certain.
可惜不是那种大家期盼的奇迹
Just not the kind of miracle one hopes to see.
大家听着 都听好了
Y'all listen. Y'all listen up here.
我们有一位客人
We're gonna have us a visitor
要和我们住一段时间
that's gonna be staying with us for a little while.
我姐姐生了个孩子 她无法抚养 所以…
My sister had a child and she couldn't see right by it, so...
他的名字叫…
He's known as...
本杰明
Benjamin.
他的身体不好 我们得好好照顾他
He's not a well child, so we're gonna have to take good care of him.
我有过10个孩子
I had 10 children.
每个我都照顾得很好 让我看看他
There's not a baby I can't care for. Let me see him.
天啊 他跟我前夫真像
God in Heaven. He looks just like my ex-husband.
看 他先天早衰
Look, he's prematurely old.
罗斯医生说他活不久
Dr. Rose said he ain't got much more time on this earth.
欢迎加入俱乐部
Join the club.
他在笑！
He's smiling!
汉伯特让我转达他的问候
Hambert sends his remembrances to you.
你疯了吗？
Are you right out of your mind?
我知道你没法有自己的孩子
I know you ain't got all the parts it takes to make one of your own,
可你也不能抚养这个
but this ain't yours to keep.
他一点都不像人
It may not even be humankind.
韦瑟斯先生 回来
Mr. Weathers, come back here.
求你了
Please.
你永远也不清楚接下来会发生什么
You never know what's coming for you.
看来我找到家了
It seemed I had found a home.
这都是真的吗？
Is any of this true?
你的声音真好听
You have such a lovely voice.
妈妈 这有张旧电车票
Mom, it's an ancient streetcar token.
那座钟一直走着
That clock just kept going,
年复一年
year after year after year.
可我不知道自己是个孩子
But I didn't know I was a child.
每天都是这些垃圾
Same old crap every day.
我以为自己和这里的人一样
I thought I was like everyone else there.
一个迟暮的老人
An old man in the twilight of his life.
你可以让他停下吗？
Could you make him stop that?
别敲叉子了 那是用来吃饭的 不是拿来玩的
Stop banging that fork. It's used for eating, not for playing with.
还有戴上餐巾 本杰明先生
And use your napkin, please, Mr. Benjamin.
奎尼！
Queenie!
嘿 小子
Hey, boy.
一直很好奇
Always had a healthy curiosity.
街上是什么样子的？下个街角又是怎样的？
What was up the street? Or around the next corner?
去抓住他！
Go get him!
本杰明！那太危险了 快回来
Benjamin! That is dangerous. Come back over here.
别动 小子
Stay put, child.
我非常爱她
I loved her very much.
她是我的母亲
She was my mother.
妈妈
Mama.
有时我觉得自己一天天地在改变
Some days I feel different than the day before.
每个人对于自己的感受都不一样
Everybody feels different about themselves, one way or another.
但是我们的终点是一样的
But we're all going the same way.
只是走的路不同罢了
Just taking different roads to get there, that's all.
你有你自己的道路 本杰明
You're on your own road, Benjamin.
妈妈？我还能活多久？
Mama? How much longer I got?
只要感谢上苍赐予你的就行了 明白吗？
Just be thankful for what you're given, hear?
你已经多活了
You're already here longer than you're supposed to.
有些晚上 我得一个人睡
Some nights, I'd have to sleep alone.
我并不介意
I didn't mind.
我在聆听这个房子的呼吸
I would listen to the house breathing.
听着大家沉睡的声音
All those people sleeping.
我感到安心
I felt safe.
这里的生活很有规律
It was a place of great routine.
每天早上5:30 不管天气如何
Every morning at 5:30, no matter the weather,
美国退伍军人温斯洛将军都会升旗
General Winslow, U.S. Army, Retired, would raise the flag.
曾经小有名气的歌剧演员 西比尔・瓦格纳夫人
Mrs. Sybil Wagner, once an opera singer of some note,
都会唱着瓦格纳的歌剧
well, she sang Wagner.
好了 孩子 过来
All right, baby, come on.
我们来给你这双老腿增加点活力
We got to put some life into these old sticks for you.
让你能走路 这样就可以帮我忙 来 明白吗？
Get you walking so you can help me out around here. Come on now, hear?
一年四季 晚餐总是在5:30准时开始
No matter the season, supper was served promptly at 5:30.
Mo-lasses （意思是糖浆 读单词中…）
Molasses.
我五岁开始学着读书
I learned to read when I was five.
我祖父曾是一个著名演员的化妆师
My grandfather was a dresser for a famous actor.
他会把每本剧本都带回来给我看
He brung home every play for me to read.
“看守我这衰弱的老头子的好人们
（选自莎士比亚《亨利六世》上篇 第二幕第五场 伦敦塔）
"Kind keepers of my weak decaying age,
“让垂死的摩提默在这儿歇一歇吧
"Let dying Mortimer here rest himself.
“我由于长期监禁 肢体痛楚不堪
"Even like a man new haled from the rack,
“好像刚从刑架上拖下来的人一般
"So fare my limbs with long imprisonment.
“我这满头白发 是在苦难的岁月中折磨出来的
"And these gray locks, the pursuivants of death,
“它预示着摩提默的死期不远了”
"Argue the end of Edmund Mortimer."
你以为我不识字 对吗？
You thought I was plain ignorant, didn't you?
我祖父侍奉的那个演员叫约翰・威尔克斯・布斯
The actor my grandfather worked for was John Wilkes Booth.
就是他杀了亚伯拉罕・林肯
He killed Abraham Lincoln.
世事难料
You never know what's coming for you.
周六晚上 妈妈会带我去教堂
On Saturday nights, Mama would make me go to church.
本杰明！
Benjamin!
- 阿门！阿门！ - 阿门！阿门！
- Amen! Amen! - Amen! Amen!
有什么需要帮忙的吗 女士？
What can I do for you, sister?
她的内部器官有问题 无法生育
Her parts are all twisted up inside and she can't have little children.
主啊 如果您能宽恕这个女人的罪行
Lord, if you could see clear to forgive this woman her sins
就让她孕育胎儿吧
so she can bear the fruit of the womb.
出来吧 该死的苦难！
Out, damnable affliction!
- 赞美主！ - 赞美主！
- Praise God! - Praise God!
哈利路亚！
Hallelujah!
- 哈利路亚！ - 哈利路亚！
- Hallelujah! - Hallelujah!
这位老人又有什么苦？
And what's this old man's irrediction?
魔鬼缠上了他
He's got the Devil on his back,
想要提早把他赶进坟墓
trying to ride him into the grave before his time.
- 出来吧 魔鬼！ - 是的！
- Out, Zebuchar! - Yes!
- Out, Beelzebub! - Yes!
你多大了？
How old are you?
七岁 可我看起来要老得多
Seven. But I look a lot older.
上帝保佑你
God bless you.
他只有七岁
He's seven.
这是一个乐观向上的人
Now, this is a man with optimism in his heart.
- 是的 - 灵魂有所信仰！
- All right. - Belief in his soul!
- 是的！ - 是的！
- Yes! - Yes!
上帝的眼中我们都是孩子！
We are all children in the eyes of God!
- 是的！ - 哈利路亚！
- Yes! - Hallelujah!
我们得帮你摆脱那个轮椅
We are gonna get you out of that chair.
- 让你能走路 - 阿门
- And we're gonna have you walk. - Amen.
没事
It's all right.
以上帝的名义…
In the name of God's glory...
站起来！
Rise up!
加油
Come on.
加油 走起来
Come on. Walk.
加油 孩子 加油
Come on, son. Come on.
- 用力 孩子 加把劲 - 加油
- Come on with it, son. Come on. - Come on.
上帝会一路看着你的
Now God is gonna see you the rest of the way.
上帝会看着这个小老人 不靠拐杖轮椅 一路走下去
He's gonna see this little old man walk without the use of a crutch or a cane.
上帝会看着你…
He's gonna see that you walk from faith...
- 哈利路亚！ - 靠着信仰和保佑一个人走下去！
- Hallelujah! ...and divine inspiration alone!
- 是的 - 嗨 本！
- Yes. - Hey, Ben!
- 去吧 孩子！ - 走走看
- Go, son! - Now walk.
- 太好了 - 继续
- Yes. - Come on.
别碰他
Don't touch him.
站起来 老家伙
Rise up, old man.
像拉撒路那样站起来
（圣经人物 被耶酥从坟墓中唤醒复活 见《圣经・约翰福音》第14章44节）
Rise up like Lazarus.
给我站起来！
I said, rise up!
哈利路亚！
Hallelujah!
是的
Yes.
加油
Come on.
说哈利路亚
Say hallelujah.
- 哈利路亚！ - 哈利路亚！
- Hallelujah! - Hallelujah!
走啊
Walk.
继续走 对
Walk on. Yes.
就是这样 本杰明
That's right, Benjamin.
每当我回想起这些 还是觉得是个奇迹
Now when I look back on it, it was miraculous.
有句话这么说的 有得必有失
But you know the saying, the Lord giveth and the Lord taketh away.
赞美主啊！
Glory in the highest!
上帝啊！
Sweet Jesus!
- 不！ - 不！
- No! - No!
这有很多人过生日
There were so many birthdays.
他真是个快乐的好人 他真是个快乐的好人…
For he's a jolly good fellow For he's a jolly good fellow...
我们一般不出门 我们会省着用蜡烛
So we wouldn't run out, we would spare the candles.
奎尼 你知道我不喜欢生日 也不喜欢蛋糕
Queenie, you know I don't like birthdays and I don't like cake.
死亡也是这里的常客 人们来到这里 又安静离去
And death was a common visitor. People came and went.
你可以感觉到有人离开了
You always knew when someone left us.
那时房子里总是寂静无声
There was a silence in the house.
这是个值得成长的美好地方
It was a wonderful place to grow up.
在这个地方 人们抛开了过往生活中的矛盾
I was with people who had shed all the inconsequences of earlier life.
每天只关心天气 洗澡水温度
Left wondering about the weather, the temperature of a bath,
一天行将结束时的阳光
the light at the end of a day.
总会有人来重新填补死者的房间
For everyone that died, someone would come to take their place.
我结过5次婚
I've been married five times.
我和我的第五任妻子 被临近的食人部落抓住了
My fifth wife and I are captured by a neighbor tribe of cannibals.
哦 天哪
Oh, goodness gracious.
我们从河里逃跑
We escaped across the river.
我的妻子不会游泳 所以很不幸被吃了
My wife, she can't swim, so, sadly, she eaten.
哦 天啊
Oh, my God.
我的第二任妻子踩到了眼镜蛇 就这么死了
My second wife steps on cobra and dies.
嫁给我真是很不幸
It was very bad luck to be married to me.
那是欧缇先生 他是我一个熟人的熟人
That's Mr. Oti. He's an acquaintance of an acquaintance of mine.
- 第二年夏天我被… - 他是个矮人
- The next summer I'm captured... - He's a Pygmy.
…巴希勒部落的人抓了 还有其他三个人
...with three others by the Baschiele tribe.
他们用我们跟一个奇怪的美国人 换了猪 鞋子和啤酒
They trade us for pigs, shoes, and beer to a very strange American man.
听说你并不像看起来那么老
I hear you're not so old as you're looking.
大家都被你耍了
You just fooling everybody.
怎么了？你有马甲本吗？
What's the matter? Did you get Madjembe?
什么是马甲本？
What's Madjembe?
虫子
Worms.
我身上没虫子
I don't think I have worms.
我就是这样的
This is just how I am.
- 今天吃药了吗？ - 没有 夫人
- Did you take your pills today? - No, ma'am.
来 喝点冰汽水
Come. Let's get a cold root beer.
我在枕头下找到了药片
I found the medication under your pillow.
我不该去 太危险了
I'm not supposed to. It's dangerous.
谁说的？来 小家伙
Who said that? Come on, little man.
孩子们好
Hello, children.
等等
Hold, please.
我和费城动物园的猴子关在一起
Then I'm in the monkey house at Philadelphia Zoological Park.
第一天就有3000人来
Three thousand people show up my first day.
看
Look.
住笼子里是什么感觉？
What's it like living in a cage?
臭死了
It stinks.
可是有猴子
But the monkeys.
他们会表演戏法
They do some tricks there.
我扔矛 和科瓦利打架
I throw a spear, wrestle with Kowali.
她是只母猩猩
She is orangutan.
不和猴子玩的时候 他们就把我赶回笼子
When I'm not playing with the monkeys, they want me to run to the bars
让我咬来咬去
in my cage, with my teeth.
之后呢？
So then what'd you do?
后来我离开了动物园 这儿走走 那儿走走 四处游荡
Then I leave zoo, go here, go there. Wandered most of the time.
独自一个人？
You were all alone?
大多数时候都是一个人的
Plenty of time you'll be alone.
像我们这样的异类 就是这样
When you're different like us, it's gonna be that way.
告诉你个小秘密
But I'll tell you a little secret.
无论什么肤色 什么体型
Fat people, skinny people, tall people,
人都是孤独的
white people, they're just as alone as we are.
但可怕的不是孤独 而是惧怕孤独
But they're scared shitless.
我想起了伴我长大的那条河
I think about the river I grew up on.
再次坐在河边感觉一定很妙
It would be nice to sit by my river again.
走吧 我约了人
Come, I have an appointment.
我的小家伙来了 准备好了吗 宝贝？
There's my little man. You ready, sugar?
时刻准备着 时刻准备着
Always ready. Always ready.
菲拉门娜 本杰明先生
Filamena, Mr. Benjamin.
- 很高兴见到你 先生 - 我的荣幸 夫人
- It's a pleasure to meet you, sir. - My pleasure, ma'am.
你认得路回家 对吗？
You can find your own way home, can't you?
乘圣查尔斯线到拿破仑路
Take the St. Charles line to Napoleon.
嘿！嘿！
Hey! Hey!
你到底去哪了？进来
Where in God's name have you been? Get in here.
我急死了 知道吗？
I mean, you take my breath away, you know that?
哦 天啊 我担心死了
Oh, Lord, I was so worried about you.
这是我过得最开心的一天
It had been the best day of my life.
- 她的呼吸情况如何？ - 很微弱
- How's her breathing? - It's shallow.
他们几小时后会到
They say it'll reach us in a few hours,
所以我得把我孩子带到姐姐那去
so I gotta get my baby and take him to my sister's.
他们说医院里没什么好担心的
They say there's nothing to worry about here in the hospital.
若需要 护士会马上过来 你还好吧？
Nurses'll be right here if you need them. Are you okay?
- 没事 我可以读书 - 一小时内我就会回来
- Yeah, I'm okay reading. - I shouldn't be more than an hour.
有人来陪了吗？
Was there just company?
是桃乐茜要走了
It was just Dorothy leaving.
继续 卡罗琳
Go on, Caroline.
“星期天 所有的家人都会来”
"On Sundays, the families would come and visit."
那是1930年的感恩节
It was Thanksgiving, 1930.
我遇见了那个改变我一生的人
I met the person who changed my life forever.
本杰明
Well, Benjamin.
你看上去真是出奇地年轻啊
Might I say you are looking strikingly youthful.
你好 富勒太太
Good day, Mrs. Fuller.
一根拐杖 背也直了
A single cane, back straight as an arrow.
你吃了什么灵丹妙药？
What elixir have you been drinking?
- 谢谢 夫人 - 奶奶！看看我！
- Thank you, ma'am. - Grandma! Look at me!
真不错
That was really something.
快过来
Come on over here, you.
这是我孙女 黛西
Now, this is my granddaughter, Daisy.
这位是…
This is Mr...
不好意思 本杰明 我还不知道你姓什么
I'm afraid, Benjamin, I don't rightly know your last name.
叫我本杰明就行了
Benjamin's fine.
我永远忘不了她那双蓝眼睛
I never forgot her blue eyes.
各位 晚餐准备好了
Good people, supper is served.
为了健康和食物 为了爱和友谊 为了上帝赐予的一切
Health and food, for love and friends. For everything thy goodness sends.
阿门
Amen.
- 阿门！ - 阿门！
- Amen! - Amen!
你们知道火鸡并不是鸟吗？
Did you know turkeys aren't really birds?
怎么说？
Why do you say that?
他们属于雉科 基本不会飞
They're in the pheasant family, can't hardly fly.
不觉得这很可怜吗？不会飞的鸟？
It's sad, don't you think? Birds that can't fly?
我喜欢不会飞的鸟
I love birds that can't fly.
非常美味
They are so delicious.
- 你太坏了 - 在我们向主感谢恩赐之时
- That's terrible. - I have something to tell y'all
我有件事要宣布
while we're giving thanks for God's blessings.
奇迹在我身上发生了
I had a miracle happen.
主回应了我的祈祷
The Lord saw fit to answer my prayers.
什么叫回应了她的祈祷？
What does she mean, answered her prayers?
谢谢 谢谢
Thanks. Thank you.
她有孩子了 傻瓜
She's gonna have a baby, silly.
我妈妈怀上弟弟的时候也这么说过
That's what my mama said when I was gonna have a baby brother,
可他没活多久
but he didn't live long,
因为他的呼吸有问题
'cause he didn't breathe right.
“下午他长出了漂亮的后腿
（选自吉卜林创作的儿童作品故事集中的老袋鼠之歌）
"In the afternoon, when he had got his beautiful hind legs
“就如大神农答应过的
"just as Big God Nqong had promised.
“时间正好是5点
"You can see that it is 5:00,
“大神农的钟上就是这样”
"because Big God Nqong's clock says so."
很神奇吧？
Isn't that something?
再讲一遍
Again, read it again.
哦 再讲一遍吧
Oh, read it again, please.
好吧 不过讲完之后 你们必须去睡觉
All right. But afterwards, you must go to bed.
我保证
I promise.
“老袋鼠”
"Old Man Kangaroo."
你睡着了吗？
Are you sleeping?
谁？
Who's that?
是我 黛西
It's me, Daisy.
哦 嗨！
Oh, hi!
过来
'Kay, come on.
我们去哪？
Where are we going?
来 到这下面
Come on. Under here.
给 把这点上
Here, you light it.
我不该玩火柴
I'm not supposed to play with matches.
别那么胆小 快点
Don't be a chicken. Light it.
我跟你说个秘密 你也跟我说个
I'll tell you a secret if you'll tell me one.
好啊
Okay.
我看见我妈妈吻了一个男人
I saw my mama kissing another man.
她脸都红了
Her face was red from it.
该你了
Your turn.
我并没有看上去那么老
I'm not as old as I look.
我也这么觉得
I thought so.
你不像个老人
You don't seem like an old person.
- 比如我奶奶那样 - 没错
- Like my grandma. - I'm not.
你病了？
Are you sick?
我听见妈妈和蒂奇私下聊天
Well, I heard Mama and Tizzy whispering.
他们说我活不久了 但或许又不是
They said I was gonna die soon, but maybe not.
你真奇怪
You're odd.
你和我见过的人不一样
You're different than anybody I've ever met.
- 可以吗？ - 当然
- May I? - Okay.
你们在下面干嘛？
What are you doing under there?
快回床上去！
You come right out here and get back up to bed!
都大半夜了！
It's after midnight!
不可以再一起玩了
You are not to be playing together.
是 夫人
Yes, ma'am.
快回床上去 小姑娘
Now you get back to bed, little lady.
你还太小 半夜不能一个人出来乱跑
You're too young to be wandering around in the night on your own.
还有你该为自己感到羞愧
And you ought to be ashamed of yourself.
你跟别的小孩不一样
You are a different child.
有着大人外表 却还是个孩子
A man-child.
孩子 别人是不会明白你的不一样的
And, baby, people aren't gonna understand just how different you are.
我怎么了 妈妈？
What's wrong with me, Mama?
过来
Come here.
上帝也没说 孩子
God hasn't said yet, baby.
快回床上 好吗？乖点
Now go on to bed, hear? And behave yourself.
去吧 别忘了祈祷 听见了吗？
Go on. Say your prayers, hear?
我跟你说过我曾被闪电击过7次吗？
Did I ever tell you I've been struck by lightning seven times?
一次是在修屋顶
Once when I was repairing a leak on the roof.
一次是在过马路取信
Once I was just crossing the road to get the mail.
我永远忘不了她那双…
I never forgot her...
“…蓝眼睛”
"...blue eyes."
妈妈？
Mom?
这个本杰明是不是对你一见钟情啊？
Did you get that this Benjamin loved you from the first time that he saw you?
很少人会有这种经历
Not many people experience that.
要我继续吗？
Want me to go on?
他划掉了一些
He crosses something out.
那个孩子到来后 一切变得不同了
When that baby came, things were different.
你妈妈走了 你爸爸还在
Your mama gone away And your daddy gonna stay
孩子也在
Didn't leave nobody but the baby
有人出生 有人死亡
Babies were born, people died.
许多人进出过那所老房子
A lot of folks been through that old house.
我是来道别的 我要走了
I've come to say goodbye. I'm going away.
走？
Going?
去哪？
Where?
还没想好
I haven't figured that out yet,
不过我会给你寄明信片
but I'll send you a postcard when I get there.
你的朋友怎么办 那个高个子的女人？
What about your friend, the tall lady?
我们已经不是朋友了
We are not friends anymore.
高个子的人有时就这样
That's what happens with tall people sometimes.
好吧 再见
Well, goodbye.
那年我就是一个人这么过来的
Spent a lot of time by myself that year.
有人吗？
Hello?
- 你好 - 我今天刚搬来
- Hi. - I'm moving in today.
欢迎 我们等你很久了
Welcome. We've been expecting you.
你能带她去卢梭太太住过的那间吗？
Can you please show her up to Mrs. Rousseau's old room?
抱歉 我们这里是不许养狗的
I'm sorry, but we usually don't allow dogs in the house.
她已经很老了 都快瞎了
Well, she's old as the hills. She's almost blind.
不会麻烦你们很久
She won't be a bother much longer.
好吧 只要不碍事待多久都行
Well, all right, long as she stays from up underfoot.
这边 夫人
Right this way, ma'am.
我想了很久也没想起她叫什么
As hard as I try, I can't remember her name.
劳森太太还是哈特福德太太
Mrs. Lawson, or Mrs. Hartford.
也许是梅普尔太太
Maybe it was Maple.
很有意思 有时候我们最记不得的人
It's funny how sometimes the people we remember the least
却印象最深
make the greatest impression on us.
我清楚记得她戴着钻戒
I do remember she wore diamonds.
总是穿得很漂亮 像要出门一样
And she always dressed in fine clothing, as if she was going out.
但她从没出过门 也没人来看她
Although she never did and nobody ever came to visit her.
她教我弹钢琴
She taught me to play the piano.
无所谓你弹奏得怎样
It's not about how well you play.
重要的是你弹琴时的感受
It's how you feel about what you're playing.
试试看
Try this.
情不自禁沉浸于音乐中
You can't help putting yourself in the music.
变化是无穷的
There were many changes.
有些看得到 有些看不到
Some you could see, some you couldn't.
比如头发会四处生长
Hair had started growing in all sorts of places,
还有很多其他的事物
along with other things.
我感觉很棒
I felt pretty good, considering.
亲爱的 痛
Darling, the pain.
好的 妈妈 我去叫护士
All right, Mom, I'll get the nurse.
看看风眼 这是强烈飓风
Look at this eye. This is a major hurricane,
飓风移动不快 伴随最大持续风…
a slow hurricane, with maximum sustained winds of...
感觉不好？
Not doing too good?
似乎没人知道该走还是该留
Nobody seems to know whether to stay or leave.
都会过去的
I'm gonna ride it out.
好了 让她舒服点
There. That should make things much easier.
道过别了吗？
Have you had a chance to say your goodbyes?
我父亲等我弟弟从博格市回来 等了四个小时
（位于美国北卡罗来纳州林肯郡）
My father waited four hours for my brother to get here from Boger City.
想见他最后一面
Couldn't go without him.
- 她看上去很安详 - 是啊
- She seems like a sweet woman. - Yeah.
我应该多陪陪她的…
I haven't had as much time with her as I would've...
- 忙吗？过来帮我下 - 失陪
- You busy? I could use your help. - Excuse me.
没关系
Sure.
奎尼会同意我跟道斯先生…
"Queenie would let me go with Mr. Daws..."
去波弗蒂角看船 （路易斯安那州扔〉匕踩诉z址）
... to Poverty Point to watch the boats go up and down the river.
这些日子不好过
These were hard times.
我跟你说过我曾被闪电击了7次吗？
Did I ever tell you I was struck by lightning seven times?
一次是在田里放牛
Once when I was in the field, just tending to my cows.
我的伙计没来
My fourth hand didn't show up.
有人想在这打工赚个2块钱吗？
Anybody want to make $2 for a day's work 'round here?
怎么了？
What's the matter?
没人想勤恳工作赚这一天的工钱？
Nobody wants to do an honest day's work for an honest day's pay?
他从不给钱
He never pays.
- 没人要做？ - 我做
- Nobody wants a job? - I do.
你不晕船吧 老头？
You got your sea legs about you, old man?
我想是的
I think.
很好 这就够了
Well, that's good enough for me.
快上船 上来就知道了
Get your ass on board. We'll sure as hell find out.
我从没这么开心过
I was as happy as I could be.
谁来帮忙！
I need a volunteer!
我什么都做
I would do anything.
是 船长！
Yes, Captain!
把鸟屎都刮了！
Scrape off all this bird shit!
马上 先生
Right away, sir.
事实上 本没报酬的我却拿到了
And I was actually gonna be paid for something I would've done for free.
他是迈克・克拉克船长
His name was Captain Mike Clark.
7岁起就在拖船上了
He'd been on a tugboat since he was seven.
上来
Get moving, then.
过来
Come here.
你还能勃起吗？
Can you still get it up?
每天早上都行
I do every morning.
就凭这根 哈？能竖得老高老硬的？
The old pole, huh? The high, hard one?
我想是的
I guess.
你上一次碰女人是什么时候？
When was the last time you had a woman?
- 从没碰过 - 从没碰过？
- Never. - Never?
我记得没有 先生
Not that I know of, sir.
等等
Wait a minute, now.
你是说你活了这么多年
You mean to say you've been on this earth however many years
还没上过女人？
and you've never had a woman?
见鬼 这是我听过最惨的事了
Damn, that's the saddest thing I've ever heard in my life.
从没碰过？
Never?
没有
No.
好吧 你得感谢老天爷让你遇上我
Well, then, by Jesus, you are coming with me.
你父亲做什么的？
What did your father do?
我从没见过我父亲
I never met my father.
你这走运的杂种
You lucky bastard.
做父亲的都想压制儿子
All fathers want to do is hold you down.
我在我父亲的船上日夜做工
Out on my father's boat, workin' the two-a-day,
这个混蛋胖子
this little, fat bastard.
别人都叫他“爱尔兰苦力”
"Tug Irish," they called him.
不过最后我终于鼓足勇气跟他说
Anyway, I finally work up the nerve and tell him,
“我不想把我的一辈子都浪费在这破船上”
"I don't want to spend the rest of my life on a goddamn tugboat."
知道我的意思吗？
You know what I'm saying?
你不想把一辈子浪费在破船上
You don't want to spend the rest of your life on a tugboat.
对！就是这样！
Absolutely! Damn right!
那你知道我爸怎么回答吗？
So you know what my father says to me?
他说 “你他妈以为自己是谁？
He says, "Who the hell do you think you are?
“你他妈以为自己能做什么？”
"What the hell do you think you can do?"
然后我告诉他
So I tell him.
“既然你问了
"Well, if you're asking,
“我想当艺术家”
"I want to be an artist."
他笑了
He laughs.
“艺术家？你就是干拖船的命 就和我一样"
"An artist? God meant for you to work a tugboat, just like me.
“老老实实地给我干活”
"And that's exactly what you're gonna do."
后来我真成了艺术家
Well, I turned myself into an artist.
一个纹身艺术家！
A tattoo artist!
这都是我自己纹的
I put on every one of these myself.
要拿走我的艺术 你得先活剥了我
You have to skin me alive to take my art away from me now.
我死后 要把自己的手臂给他
When I'm dead, I'm gonna send him my arm.
那条
That one.
让别人去说吧
Don't let anyone tell you different.
想做什么就去做
You gotta do what you're meant to do.
我碰巧就成了他妈的艺术家
And I happen to be a goddamned artist.
可你还是个拖船船长
But you're a tugboat captain.
迈克船长？
Captain Mike?
我们已经为你和你的朋友准备好了
We're ready for you and your friend.
走吧 老家伙 去破你的身吧
Let's go, old timer, eh? Break your cherry.
- 好啊 甜心们！ - 嗨 船长
- Hello, my lovelies! - Hey, Captain.
- 嗨 船长 - 嗨
- Hi, Captain. - Hi.
- 嗨 - 嗨
- Hi. - Hi.
好恶心 我才不要
He gives me the willies. That is not for me.
今晚过得如何 老爷爷？
How are you tonight, grandpa?
那是一个难忘的夜晚
It was a night to remember.
你是什么 狄克・崔西还是什么？ 我得休息休息
（根据美国畅销漫画书改编拍摄的大型侦探片中的主角）
What are you, Dick Tracy or something? I've got to rest.
再来
Again.
- 谢谢 - 不 该谢谢你 你今晚过得不错
- Thank you. - No, thank you. You have a nice night.
- 明天你还在吗？ - 除了星期天每天都在
- Will you be here tomorrow? - Every night but Sunday.
我想我明白了挣钱的重要
It sure made me understand the value of earning a living.
晚安 宝贝 再来哦
Good night, sweetie. Come back now.
钱能买到一切
Things money can buy you.
外面脏
It's nasty out.
要搭车吗？
Can I offer you a ride somewhere?
您真是太好了 先生
Well, that's awfully kind of you, sir.
我叫托马斯 托马斯・巴顿
My name is Thomas, Thomas Button.
- 我叫本杰明 - 本杰明
- I'm Benjamin. - Benjamin.
很高兴认识你
It's a pleasure to know you.
愿意停下去喝杯吗？
Would you like to stop somewhere and have a drink?
好啊
All right.
晚上好 巴顿先生
Evening, Mr. Button.
要点什么 先生？
What'll it be, sir?
- 跟他一样 - 给我们都来萨泽拉克鸡尾酒
- I'll have whatever he's having. - Sazerac for the both of us.
加威士忌 不要白兰地
With whiskey, not brandy.
你不喝酒？
You don't drink, do you?
- 今晚什么都是第一次啊 - 怎么说？
- It's a night for firsts. - How's that?
以前从没找过妓女
I've never been to a brothel, either.
这是种经历
Well, it's an experience.
当然 凡事总有第一次
It certainly is. There's a time for everything.
- 没错 - 你们的酒
- True enough. - Your drinks.
恕我冒昧 你的手 痛吗？
I don't mean to be rude, but your hands. Is that painful?
我生来就有些病
Well, I was born with some form of disease.
什么病？
What kind of disease?
我天生就是老头
I was born old.
- 抱歉 - 没关系
- I'm sorry. - No need to be.
年老没什么错
There's nothing wrong with old age.
我妻子多年前去世了
My wife passed away many years ago.
非常抱歉
I'm so, so sorry.
难产死的
She died in childbirth.
- 敬孩子 - 敬母亲
- To children. - To mothers.
你干哪行的 巴顿先生？
What line of work you in, Mr. Button?
纽扣 巴顿纽扣公司 我们生产各类纽扣
Buttons. Button's Buttons. There isn't a button that we don't make.
我们最大的竞争对手是B.F.富善公司
Our biggest competition is B.F. Goodrich
还有他们该死的拉链
and his infernal zippers.
先生们还要来点什么吗？
Would you gentlemen like anything else?
再来杯上路 本杰明？
One for the road, Benjamin?
这次算我的 巴顿先生
Only if you let me pay for it, Mr. Button.
那你是干哪行的？
So, what line of work do you do?
我是个拖船工人
I'm a tugboat man.
跟你聊天很开心
I enjoyed talking to you.
跟你喝酒也很开心
I enjoyed drinking with you.
本杰明？
Benjamin?
我可以不时过来看看你吗？
Would you mind if, time to time, I stopped by and said hello?
随时欢迎 晚安 巴顿先生
Anytime. Good night, Mr. Button.
晚安 本杰明
Good night, Benjamin.
开车
Drive on.
你去哪了？
Where have you been?
没什么 遇到了个人 听了会音乐
Nothing. I met some people and listened to some music.
哦 天啊 孩子！
Oh, sweet Jesus, boy!
长大是件很有意思的事 不经意间就发生了
Growing up's a funny thing. Sneaks up on you.
本来是这样一个人 然后突然间变成了另一个人
One person is there, then suddenly somebody else has taken her place.
不再是原来那样子
She wasn't all elbows and knees anymore.
本杰明！过来！
Benjamin! Come on!
来了
Okay.
我喜欢那些周末 她会来这里
I loved those weekends when she'd come
和她的奶奶共度晚上
and spend the night with her grandmother.
黛西 黛西
Daisy. Daisy.
给你看些东西？
You want to see something?
不过你得保密 快穿好衣服 我在外面等你
You gotta keep it a secret, so get dressed. I'll meet you out back.
快点
Come on.
- 你会游泳吗？ - 你会的我也会
- Can you swim? - I can do anything you can do.
给 穿上 我们得动作快点
Here, put this on. We gotta hurry.
他还好吗？
Is he okay?
船长？
Captain?
迈克船长？
Captain Mike?
早上好 船长 能带我们出海吗？
Morning, Captain. Can you take us out?
知道今天星期几吗？
Do you know what day it is?
星期天？
Sunday?
知道那表示什么吗？
Do you know what that means?
意味着我昨晚喝醉了
Means I was very drunk last night.
你哪天不喝醉
Well, you're drunk every night.
- 是个女孩？ - 好朋友
- Is that a girl? - Close friend.
我想带她看河
I want to show her the river.
你别偷偷带外人出海
You're not supposed to go joyriding with civilians.
我会丢掉执照的
I could lose my license.
你还等什么？
What are you waiting for?
要进站维修了
Pulled in for repair a wounded duck.
她在飞了 哈？
She's flying now, huh?
喂 水手！
Ahoy, sailor!
真希望能和他们一起去
I wish we could go with them.
你在说什么 妈妈？
Did you say something, Mom?
天气越来越糟
It's getting really bad.
能听见吗 妈妈？
Can you hear me, Mom?
我没多少时间了
Time just seeped out of me.
“变化太快”
"Things were changing quickly."
不知怎么回事 可你的头发多了
I don't know how it's possible, but you seem to have more hair.
要是我告诉你我没有变老
What if I told you that I wasn't getting older,
而是变得更年轻了呢？
but I was getting younger than everybody else?
那真不幸
Well, I'd feel sorry for you,
你必须看着你爱的人先你而去
to have to see everybody you love die before you do.
真是可怕的责任
It's an awful responsibility.
我以前从没想过生死
I'd never thought about life or death that way before.
本杰明 我们命中注定要失去所爱之人
Benjamin, we're meant to lose the people we love.
不然我们怎么知道 他们在我们生命中有多重要？
How else would we know how important they are to us?
秋天的一天 死神不期而至
And one fall day, a familiar visitor came knocking on our door.
跟我一起去杂货店吗？
You want to go with me to the drugstore?
她教我弹钢琴
She taught me how to play the piano.
- 阿门 - 阿门
- Amen. - Amen.
她让我明白了失去一个人的感觉
And she taught me what it meant to miss somebody.
走吧
Let's go.
我去过妓院
I had gone to a brothel.
我喝过酒
I'd had my first drink.
跟一个朋友道别 跟另一个朋友永别
Said goodbye to one friend and buried another.
1936年我人生的第17个年末
In 1936, when I was coming to the end of the 17th year of my life,
我收拾了行装跟大家告别
I packed my bag, said goodbye.
- 再见 本杰明 - 再见
- Bye, Benjamin. - Goodbye.
我知道 生活仍将继续 也许我再也见不到他们了
I knew, life being what it was, I'd probably never see them again.
再见 本杰明先生
Bye, Mr. Benjamin.
- 祝你好运 儿子 - 谢谢
- Good luck to you, son. - Thank you.
- 我爱你 妈妈 - 我也爱你 宝贝
- I love you, Mama. - I love you, too, baby.
别忘了每晚做祈祷 好吗？
I want you to say your prayers every night, hear?
平平安安的 听见了吗？
Be safe, hear?
本杰明！
Benjamin!
- 你去哪？ - 出海
- Where you going? - To sea.
我会给你寄明信片的
I'll send you a postcard.
无论在哪
From everywhere.
无论在哪都要给我寄明信片
Write me a postcard from everywhere.
你能想象吗？
Can you imagine?
无论他去哪 在什么地方工作
He sent me a postcard from everywhere he went.
都会给我寄明信片
Every place he worked.
纽芬兰 巴芬湾
Newfoundland. Baffin Bay.
格拉斯哥 利物浦 纳尔维克
Glasgow. Liverpool. Narvik.
他和迈克船长一起去的
He had gone with that Captain Mike.
迈克船长和莫兰兄弟拖船打捞公司
Captain Mike had contracted for three years
签了3年的合约
with Moran Brothers Tug and Salvage.
旧船装上了柴油机和新的绞车
The old ship had been refitted with a diesel engine and a new sea winch.
我们绕过了佛罗里达 沿着大西洋海岸北上
We went around Florida and up the Atlantic seaboard.
船上现在有7名船员了 迈尔船长和我
We were a crew of seven now. Captain Mike and me.
厨师 来自特拉华州威灵顿的普兰提斯・梅斯
Cookie, Prentiss Mayes from Wilmington, Delaware.
布罗迪双胞胎 里克和维克
The Brody twins, Rick and Vic,
在海上这兄弟俩相处很好 但不知什么原因
who got along fine at sea but, for some reason,
一旦回到陆地 他们就不对盘
once they were on dry land couldn't stand the sight of each other.
你知道的 每八艘船就有一艘永远回不来
You know, one in every eight boats never returns.
一个叫约翰・格林的 人如其名
There was John Grimm, who sure fit his name.
全体船员在海上失踪了
All hands lost at sea.
来自南达科他州的贝尔维迪市
From Belvedere, South Dakota.
还有来自北卡罗来纳州阿什维尔的 普莱森特・柯蒂斯
And Pleasant Curtis from Asheville, Notch.
从不跟人说话 除了他自己
Never said a word to anyone, except himself.
我经常给他写信
I wrote him constantly.
我告诉他我受邀参加纽约市
I told him I had been invited to audition in New York City
一所美国芭蕾学校的面试
for the School of American Ballet.
请留下
Please stay.
谢谢 谢谢
Thank you. Thank you.
你可以留下来
You can stay.
可我在团里并不出名
But I was relegated to the corps.
只不过是个跳舞的流浪者
Another dancing gypsy.
本杰明！
Benjamin!
第一次见你时
How is it when you showed up
你比那个系船柱大不了多少 还一只脚踩进了棺材
you were no bigger than a bollard with one foot in the grave,
而现在 是我喝多了
but now, either I drink a hell of a lot more than I think I do,
还是你长个了？
or you sprouted?
你有什么秘密？
What's your secret?
船长
Well, Captain,
你确实喝多了
you do drink a lot.
我们住在一个小旅馆里 名字不错 叫冬宫
We stayed in a small hotel with a grand name, The Winter Palace.
你根本不知道自己在说什么
You have no idea what you're talking about.
蜂鸟不是一般的鸟类
The hummingbird is not just another bird.
它的心率达到每分钟1200下
Its heart rate's 1,200 beats per minute.
它的翅膀每秒扇动80次
Its wings beat 80 times a second.
要是让它无法扇动翅膀
If you was to stop their wings from beating,
不到10秒就会死掉
it would be dead in less than 10 seconds.
这不是一般的鸟
This is no ordinary bird.
简直就是奇迹
This is a frickin' miracle.
人们用影像慢放扇翅膀的动作
They slowed down their wings with moving pictures,
知道他们看到了什么？
and you know what they saw?
它们的翼尖像这样运动
Their wingtips are doing that.
知道数字8有什么数学含义吗？
You know what the figure eight is the mathematical symbol for?
无穷
Infinity.
无穷！
Infinity!
每个人 不论语言和肤色有何差异
Everybody, no matter what differences they had,
却都有一个共同点
the languages, the color of their skin, had one thing in common.
每晚都会喝醉
They were drunk every single night.
三楼 谢谢
Three, please.
能等一下吗 亲爱的？
Could you hold, dear, for us, please?
非常感谢 晚上好
Thank you very much. Good evening.
她叫伊丽莎白・艾伯特
Her name was Elizabeth Abbott.
她并不漂亮 很平凡
She was not beautiful. She was plain as paper.
但在我看来她很美
But she was pretty as any picture to me.
你在看什么？
What are you looking at?
你该知道 我们有个长期协议
If you must know, we have a longstanding agreement
不醉不归
never to go to bed sober.
- 对吗 亲爱的？ - 随你怎么说 亲爱的
- Isn't that right, darling? - Whatever you say, darling.
她丈夫是沃尔特・艾伯特
Her husband was Walter Abbott.
他是英国贸易代表团在摩尔曼斯克的首席部长
He was Chief Minister of the British Trade Mission in Murmansk,
而且他还是个间谍
and he was a spy.
- 亲爱的 - 哦 谢谢 亲爱的
- Darling. - Oh, thank you, my darling.
- 钥匙 亲爱的 - 噢 对
- Key, darling. - Oh, yes.
我的一只鞋跟断了
I broke my heel off one of my shoes.
我不习惯只穿袜子走路
I'm not in the habit of walking about in my stocking feet.
那里白天很长
They were long days there.
夜晚更加漫长
And even longer nights.
有一个晚上 我辗转难眠
One particular night, I was having trouble sleeping.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
我睡不着
I couldn't sleep.
我要去泡些茶 你要吗？
I was gonna make some tea. Would you like some?
哦 不用了 谢谢
Oh, no. Thank you.
牛奶？还是蜂蜜？
Milk? Honey?
一点蜂蜜 谢谢
A bit of honey, please.
我希望你不介意蜂蜜里有苍蝇
I hope you like flies in your honey.
哦 还是算了
Oh, perhaps not.
哦 也许多浸一会会更好
Oh, maybe better to let it steep a little.
浸？
Steep?
浸泡
Soak.
我不知道 我的意思是 泡茶就该这样
I don't know, I mean, there's a proper way of making tea.
我家乡那都喜欢喝热茶
Well, where I'm from, people just want it to be hot.
这样啊
Well, quite right.
- 现在你是海员 - 水手
- Now, you're a seaman. - A sailor.
希望你不要介意 我忍不住想问
I hope you won't think me impolite, but I have to ask,
作为一个水手你是不是有点老？
aren't you a little old to be working on a boat?
没有年龄限制 只要你能做
There's no age limit, as long as you can do the work.
你睡不好是吗？谢谢
And you have trouble sleeping? Thank you.
以前不这样 通常我睡得像婴儿一样沉
I didn't think I did. I usually sleep like a baby.
有些事让我睡不着
Something's been keeping me up.
我父亲80岁的时候
My father, in his 80s,
深信自己会在睡眠中死去
he was so convinced he was gonna die in his sleep,
他约束自己只睡午觉
he limited himself to having afternoon naps.
他坚信自己可以逃脱死亡
He was so determined he was gonna cheat death.
- 他做到了吗？ - 做到什么？
- Did he? - Did he what?
睡觉时死了？
Die in his sleep?
他死在自己最喜欢的椅子上
He died sitting in his favorite chair
听着自己最喜欢的广播节目
listening to his favorite program on the wireless.
他一定已经知道了
He must have known something.
我的丈夫是英国贸易部长 我们已经在这呆了14个月了
My husband's the British Trade Minister, and we've been here for 14 months.
- 天哪  - 本来我们要去北京的
- Good God. - We were supposed to go to Peking
可是看来永远都无法成行了
but it never seemed to work out.
你去过远东吗？
Have you been in the Far East?
没有 事实上我哪也没去过
No. I've never been anywhere, really.
我是说 港口以外的地方
I mean, outside of harbors.
你从哪来？
And where is it that you're from?
路易斯安那州新奥尔良
New Orleans. Louisiana.
我知道那个地方
I didn't know there was another.
她跟我讲了她去过的地方 还有她的所见所闻
And she told me about all the places she had been, and what she had seen.
我们一直聊到天亮
And we talked till just before the dawn.
我只是一个酒鬼
I'm just a lush, myself.
我们回到各自的房间 过各自的生活
And we went back to our rooms, to our separate lives.
可每晚我们都会在大厅见面
But every night, we'd meet again in that lobby.
午夜的旅馆是一个神奇的地方
A hotel in the middle of the night can be a magical place.
老鼠在远处跑跑停停
A mouse running, and stopping.
暖气炉发出嘶嘶的响声
A radiator hissing.
窗帘在沙沙作响
A curtain blowing.
这样的场景让你感到安静 甚至是温暖
There's something peaceful, even comforting
你知道你所爱的人此刻正在熟睡之中
knowing that the people you love are asleep in their beds
而没有什么可以伤害到他们
where nothing can harm them.
伊丽莎白和我都忘记了时间
Elizabeth and I would lose track of the night
直到黎明的到来
until just before daybreak.
我想我可能让你误解了
I think I may have given you the wrong impression.
什么？
Beg pardon?
已婚女人通常不会在半夜
Well, married women don't customarily sit around
和陌生男人呆在旅馆里
in the middle of the night with strange men in hotels.
我不知道已婚女人什么该做 什么不该做
I wouldn't know what a married woman does or doesn't do.
晚安
Good night.
摩尔曼斯克
Murmansk.
“我遇见了一个人 我坠入了爱河”
"I've met somebody, and I've fallen in love."
妈妈？
Mom?
那是60多年前的事了
That was over 60 years ago.
你爱他吗 妈妈？
Did you love him, Mother?
小女孩哪懂什么爱情？
What does a girl know about love?
呃…
Well...
- 我穿得不好 - 哦 看起来蛮好 这才像你
- I'm not dressed. - Oh, you look splendid, just as you are.
在摩尔曼斯克 别浪费时间在酒和奶酪上
Don't waste any time bothering about the wine or the cheese in Murmansk,
因为这些实在很平常
'cause they're really completely ordinary,
但是鱼子酱和伏特加
but the caviar and the vodka
更显高贵奢华
are sublime and plentiful.
那么
So.
好好尝尝
Savor it.
别一下子全吃了
And don't eat it all at once,
因为那样是享受不到什么的
because that way, there's nothing left to enjoy.
现在 口含伏特加 咽下一点点
And now, take a little swallow of vodka while it's still in your mouth.
你相处过的女人不多吧？
You haven't been with many women, have you?
星期天不多
Not on Sundays.
你以前从没吃过鱼子酱 对吧？
And you've never had caviar before, have you?
是的 夫人
No, ma'am.
我19岁时
When I was 19,
试图成为第一个游过英吉利海峡的女人
I attempted to become the first woman ever to swim the English Channel.
真的？
Really?
但那天的水流很急
But the current that day was so strong that,
向前游一下 被水流推后两下
for every stroke I took, I was pushed back two.
我在水里待了32小时
I was in the water for 32 hours.
距离加来两英里时
And when I was two miles from Calais,
天开始下雨了
it started to rain.
就是这样！保持平稳！
That's it! Steady on!
我实在游不动时
When I couldn't go any further,
我停下了
I stopped.
我只好停下
I just stopped.
别人都问我 要不要再来一次？
And everybody asked me, would I try again?
为什么不呢？
For why wouldn't I?
可我再没有试过
But I never did.
事实上 自那以后我没做过什么
As a matter of fact, I've never done anything with my life after that.
你的手好粗糙
Your hands are so coarse.
我能感觉到吹向你脸颊的海风
I can feel the wind in your cheek.
恐怕已经到午夜了
I'm afraid it's the witching hour.
那是第一次有女人吻我
It was the first time a woman had ever kissed me.
难以忘怀
It's something you never forget.
是你让我感觉年轻了
I think you make me feel younger.
你也让我觉得年轻了好几岁
You make me feel years younger, too.
希望如此
I wish I was.
我会改变很多事
So many things I'd change.
我会弥补所有的过错
I'd undo all my mistakes.
什么过错？
What mistakes?
我一直等着 知道吗？
I kept waiting, you know?
想着做些什么改变自己的状况
Thinking that I'd do something to change my circumstances.
做些什么
Do something.
那些浪费掉的 一去不复返
Such an awful waste. You never get it back.
人生就这么平白无辜地浪费了
Wasted time.
如果我们在一起
If we're going to have an affair,
白天千万不要见面
you're never to look at me during the day.
日出之前我们一定要分开
And we're always to part before sunrise.
永远不要说“我爱你”
And we will never say "I love you."
这些是规则
Those are the rules.
- 你冷吗？ - 快冻僵了
- Are you cold? - I'm freezing.
哦 你！你快冻僵了
Oh, you! You're frozen.
真傻 我还穿着皮衣呢 我怎么这么粗心
What an idiot, I'm standing here in this fur. How thoughtless of me.
她是第一个爱过我的女人
She was the first woman that ever loved me.
要我跳过一些内容吗？
You want me to skip some?
不用 我很高兴有人能温暖他
No, I'm glad he had somebody to keep him warm.
“我等不及要再见到她”
"I couldn't wait to see her again."
我们每晚见面
We saw each other every night.
总是在同一间屋子
We always used the same room.
可每次都有不同的体验
But each time seemed new and different.
过来
Come here.
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth.
晚安
Good night.
直到有一个晚上
Until one night.
昨天 1941年12月7日
Yesterday, December 7th, 1941,
耻辱的一天…
a date which will live in infamy...
这是一场会议 一场事关未来的政治性会议
It's a meeting, a policy meeting regarding your future,
可能不止如此
possibly beyond.
伙计们 计划有变
There's been a change of plan, lads.
你们或许知道 或许不知道
As you may or may not know,
日本人昨天轰炸了珍珠港
the Japs bombed Pearl Harbor yesterday.
富兰克林・德拉诺・罗斯福 要求我们每个人尽到自己的职责
Frank D. Roosevelt's asked each of us to do our part.
切尔西号被美国海军征用
The Chelsea's been commissioned to serve in the United States Navy.
负责维修 打捞和营救
To repair, to salvage, and to rescue.
有谁不想打仗 现在说还来得及
Anybody doesn't want to go to war, now is the time to say so.
只要你踏上了那艘船 你就是海军了 朋友
Once you set foot on that boat, you're in the Navy, friend.
我一直想和你谈谈 迈克
Yeah, I've been meaning to talk with you, Mike.
我老婆的情况不好
My wife's doing poorly.
我希望能再见她一面
I'd like to maybe see her one more time.
你现在可以自由地回家了 梅斯先生
You're free to make your way home any way you can, Mr. Mayes.
他走了谁做饭啊？
Well, if he's leaving, who's gonna cook?
食物中毒是海上人员死亡的最主要原因之一
Food poisoning's one of the leading causes of death at sea.
仅次于安全装备不足
Right after inadequate safety equipment.
我会做饭 船长 干了一辈子了
I can cook, Captain. Been doing it all my life.
我不知道 你也厌战 本杰明
I don't know. You're a little moody for war, Benjamin.
管他呢？
What the hell?
想打倒小日本和匈奴人的都跟我走
I'll take any man wants to kick the shite out of the Japs and the Huns.
就这样吧 收拾行装 我们要上战场了 先生们！
That's it, pack your gear. We're going to war, gentlemen!
她留了纸条
She had left a note.
她写道 “能遇到你真好”
She wrote, "It was nice to have met you."
就这样
And that was it.
战争和我们想象的不一样
It wasn't the war any of us expected.
我们只是拖走破损的船 其实都是些废铜烂铁
We would just tow crippled ships, scraps of metal, really.
真有战争 我们也没看到
If there was a war, we didn't see it.
派给我们的主炮手非常热爱海军
There was a man assigned to us. The Chief Gunner loved the Navy.
最重要的是他爱美国
But most of all, he loved America.
世界上没有其他国家
There is no other country in the world.
当你拼写美国…
When you spell America...
他叫丹尼斯・史密斯 是个纯血统的切罗基人 （美洲土著人）
His name was Dennis Smith, and he was a full-blooded Cherokee.
他的家族在美洲居住了500多年
His family had been Americans for over 500 years.
去他们的和平主义者 说什么不会凭良心打仗
These pacifists. They say they won't fight on conscience.
要是所有人都凭良心
Now, where would be if everybody decided to act
- 那会怎么样？ - 冷静点 长官？
- according to their conscience? - Keep it down, would you, Chief?
嘿 我观察你很久了
Hey. I've been watching you.
你看上去值得信任
You seem trustworthy.
万一我有什么不测
If something happens to me,
你能答应把这个给我老婆吗？
could you see that this gets to my wife?
他把全部工钱都给了我 一分钱也没花过
He'd given me all of his pay. Hadn't spent a dime of it.
我希望家人知道 我时刻挂念着他们
I want my family to know I was thinking about them.
全体船员到甲板上！
All hands on deck!
快起来 你们这群懒猪！
Get your asses up here, you lazy bastards!
战争终于还是来了
The war had finally found us.
都别动！
All stop!
普莱森特 转下那灯
Pleasant, man that light.
一艘载有1300人的运输舰被鱼雷击沉
A transport carrying 1,300 men had been split by a torpedo.
我们是第一个赶到现场的
We were first to arrive at the scene.
- 关掉引擎！ - 都别动！
- Cut the engines! - All stop!
四周只有我们的声音
We were the only sound.
伙计们！
Fellas!
潜水艇！
Sub!
我们绝对跑不过他们
We sure as hell can't outrun them fuckers.
各就各位！
Battle stations!
谢谢 长官
Thank you, Chief.
什么？
What?
是最后一个么？
Is that the last one?
船长！
Captain!
狗日的把我的画打烂了！
They shot the hell out of my painting!
握着我的手
Give me your other hand.
你会没事的 船长
You'll be all right, Captain.
天使们在天堂里 给你留了个好地方呢
They got a nice spot in Heaven waiting for you. Nice spot.
不顺心的时候 你可以像疯狗一样发狂
You can be as mad as a mad dog at the way things went.
可以破口大骂 诅咒命运
You could swear, curse the Fates.
但到头来
But when it comes to the end,
还是得放手
you have to let go.
船长？
Captain?
那天 1328人离开了人间
Thirteen hundred and twenty eight men died that day.
我和切罗基人丹尼斯・史密斯道别
I said my goodbyes to the Cherokee, Dennis Smith.
和约翰・格林道别--他猜得没错 他最后还是死在那儿了
John Grimm, who was right, he was gonna die there.
我把普莱森特・柯蒂斯的钱 寄给了他妻子
I sent Pleasant Curtis' wife his money.
我向双胞胎的维克・布罗迪道别
I said goodbye to the twin, Vic Brody,
还有迈克・克拉克--切尔西号的船长
and to Mike Clark, captain of the tugboat Chelsea.
我和那些仍旧怀揣梦想的人道别
I said goodbye to all the other men who had dreams of their own,
他们有的想做保险推销员
all the men who wanted to be insurance salesmen
有的想当医生 律师 甚至是部落酋长
or doctors or lawyers or Indian chiefs.
这个修不好了
This don't get fixed.
在那儿 死亡不再是自然发生的了
Out here, death didn't seem natural.
我从没在远海上见过蜂鸟
I'd never seen a hummingbird that far out to sea.
无论是之前 还是此后
Before or since.
1945年5月 我26岁
And in May of 1945, when I was 26 years old,
我回家了
I came home.
我准备好了！准备好了！
I'm ready! I'm ready!
来了！
I'm coming!
- 我准备好了！ - 这就来了 阿法莉娜
- I'm ready! - All right, I'm coming, Miss Alfalina.
- 奎尼？ - 嗯？
- Queenie? - Yes?
老天爷！你回来了！ 神啊 你回来了！
Sweet Jesus! Oh, you're home! Oh, Lord, you came back!
- 快让我瞧瞧 - 他是谁呀 妈妈？
- Let me look at you. - Who's that, Mama?
- 孩子啊 这是你哥哥 本杰明 - 我都不知道我还有哥哥
- Child, it's your brother, Benjamin. - I didn't know he was my brother.
你不知道的事情多了去了 小丫头
There's a shitload of things you don't know, child.
赶紧去把地扫完
Get on out there and finish sweeping.
再把手洗洗来帮我摆餐桌 快去
Come here, wash your hands, help me with the table. Go on, now.
转过来 你看起来跟重生了一样！
Turn around. You look like you've been born again.
比春天还有活力！
Younger than the springtime.
要我说 那牧师施法的时候 肯定是又给了你一条命
I think that preacher laid hands on you gave you a second life.
那会我看着你就知道 你跟别人不一样
I knew it that moment I saw you, you were special.
知道嘛 我的膝盖现在都酸
I tell you what, my knees are sore,
因为我每天晚上都跪着 求上帝保佑
'cause I've been on them every night asking the Lord,
求他“上帝啊 我只要他平安回家”
I said, "God, just bring him home safely."
还记得我怎么跟你说的吗？
Remember what I told you?
“你永远都猜不到 以后的生活是啥样子”
"You never know what's coming for you"?
没错 快坐下
That's right. Sit down.
这几年 有碰上什么有趣儿的事吗？
Well, you learn anything worth repeating?
- 当然了 - 你尝过了苦头
- I sure saw some things. - Oh, you seen some pain.
- 也尝过甜头？ - 嗯
- Some joy, too? - Sure. Sure, I did.
我就是想听你亲口说这些 瞧瞧你呀
Yeah, that's what I want to hear. Look at you.
- 蒂奇上哪儿去了？ - 哦 孩子
- Where's Tizzy? - Oh, baby.
韦瑟斯走了 上个月 睡觉的时候去的
Mr. Weathers died in his sleep one night last April.
- 妈妈 您节哀 - 别操心我了 孩子
- Mama, I'm so sorry. - Don't you worry about that, baby.
现在还活着的也就那么一两个
Yeah, well, it's only one or two of them left now.
不过都还挺乐呵
They all just about new.
他们应该和别人一样 也都在等着那一天吧
Guess they're waiting their turn like everybody else, huh?
你能回家陪我 我就知足了！
I'm so glad you're back home with me!
咱得赶紧给你找个媳妇 再找个工作 就这么定了！
Now, we're gonna have to find you a wife and a new job! That's right.
快进来 帮我摆桌子
Come on in here, help me with this table.
本杰明
Benjamin.
别费劲了 她全聋了
You're wasting your time, baby. She's stone deaf.
你住以前德瑟罗住的房间
Oh, and you'll be staying in what was Mrs. DeSeroux's old room.
你太大个了 再和别人挤一间可不像话
You're too big to be rooming with anybody else.
回家的感觉 很奇妙
It's a funny thing about coming home.
一切看起来都是一样的 闻起来也是 摸起来也是
Looks the same, smells the same, feels the same.
我说没说过 我被闪电击中过七次？
Did I ever tell you I've been struck by lightning seven times?
有一次我就那么好端端地开着车 心里想着自己的事
Once when I was sitting in my truck, just minding my own business.
我才意识到 其实变的 只有你自己
You realize what's changed is you.
我回来后不久的某个清晨…
And late one morning, not long after I'd been back...
谢谢
Thank you.
嘿
Hey.
- 请问 奎尼在吗？ - 黛西？
- Excuse me, is Queenie here? - Daisy?
- 是我啊 本杰明 - 本杰明？
- It's me, Benjamin. - Benjamin?
哦 天！
Oh, my God!
真的是你！本杰明！
Of course it's you! Benjamin!
你过得怎么样？ 咱们太久没见了！
How are you? It's been such a long time.
我有好多事情要问你 你什么时候回来的？
There's so much I want to know. When did you get back?
我回来也没几周
Well, I got back a few weeks ago.
我上次问奎尼 她说你还在打仗 说是在海上的哪儿
I spoke to Queenie, she said you were in the war, somewhere at sea.
- 我们都担心死你了 - 哦 我挺好的
- We were so, so worried about you. - Oh, I'm okay.
瞧瞧你啊 真是好看
Well, look at you. You're so lovely.
你后来就不给我写信了
You stopped writing.
“我离开的时候 她还只是个小女孩 如今 却已出落成了窈窕淑女”
"When I had left, she was a girl. And a woman had taken her place.
“她是我所见过的人中 最美的女子”
"She was the most beautiful woman I'd ever seen."
美
Beautiful.
是“最美”
"The most beautiful."
- 你还记得富勒奶奶吗？ - 当然了 怎么了？
- You remember Grandma Fuller? - Why, sure I do.
- 她过世了 - 我听说了 节哀
- She passed. - I heard that. I'm sorry.
真不敢想 我们又见面了 这一定是缘分
I just can't believe we're both here. Must be fate.
不对不对 他们管这叫什么来着？
No, no, what do they call it?
天意
Kismet.
你知道埃德加・西吗？ 就是那个会通灵的？
Do you know about Edgar Cayce, the psychic?
应该没…
I don't believe I...
他说 万事万物都是注定的
He says that everything is predetermined,
不过我宁愿把这当成缘分
but I like to think of it as fate.
虽然也搞不懂这到底是怎么回事 我还是很高兴咱们重逢了
I'm not sure how it works, but I'm glad it happened.
你去过曼哈顿吗？ 就在我住的地方河对面
Have you been to Manhattan? It's right across the river from me.
要是我站在床上
Now, I can see the Empire State Building
就可以望见帝国大厦
if I stand on my bed.
说说你吧？你都去哪了？
What about you? Where have you been?
全都告诉我 上次你写信说 你去俄国了
Tell me everything. Last time you wrote, you said you'd been to Russia.
我一直想去那呢 那儿真像别人说的那么冷吗？
I've always wanted to go to Russia. Is it as cold as they say?
- 冷多了 - 我的天呀
- Twice as cold. - My goodness.
大家嘴上都说你不一样 我可是真的觉得你不是一般人
We always said you were different. But I think you really are.
你还说你遇上了你喜欢的人 最后有结果吗？
You wrote that you met somebody. Did it work out?
还是没成
It ran its course.
嘿 还记得这个吗？
Hey, do you remember this?
“照片里画的是大袋鼠
"This is the picture of Old Man Kangaroo
下午五点 他终于会蹦蹦跳了”
"at 5:00 in the afternoon."
一起吃个晚饭好吗？
Would you like to have dinner?
我有没有跟你说过 我跟着巴兰钦跳舞呀？ （著名芭蕾舞导演）
Did I tell you that I danced for Balanchine?
他可是个有名的编舞大师 他说我的线条很完美
Oh, he's a famous choreographer. He said that I had perfect line.
知道吗 有一个排练 有人摔倒
You know, in a rehearsal once, a dancer fell.
然后他…就把这个动作 编进舞蹈里去了！
And he just... He just put it right into the production.
你能想象那情形吗？ 在一部…经典芭蕾舞剧里
I mean, can you imagine that? Like in a... In a classical ballet?
让一个演员 故意跌倒
You know, a dancer, intentionally falling.
如今形容舞蹈有个新词了 叫“抽象”
There's a whole new word for dance now. It's called "abstract."
当然了 有名的大师不止他一个
No, he's not the only one, though.
还有林肯・柯尔斯坦 露西亚・切斯 哦 对…
There's Lincoln Kirstein and Lucia Chase, and oh, my...
还有阿格尼・德・米尔
Oh, there's Agnes de Mille.
她根本就不管什么条条框框
She's just torn up all those conventions,
就是“抬头挺胸”那一套
you know, all that straight-up-and-down stuff.
她说舞蹈最重要的不是形式 而是舞者的感觉
It's not about the formality of the dance, it's about what the dancer's feeling.
她跟我说的这些 就像是另一个全新的世界
As she told me about this big new world,
那些名字 对我来说 啥也不是
names that didn't mean a thing to me,
其实她说什么 我也没怎么听进去
I didn't really hear very much of what she was saying.
一切都是全新的 现代的 美式的！
It's new and it's modern and it's American.
只有他们了解我们的活力和形体
They understand our vigor and our physicality.
哦 天 我是不是说太多了呀
Oh, my God. I've just been talking and talking.
没有没有 我喜欢听你讲 我不知道你还抽烟
No, no, I've enjoyed listening. I didn't know you smoked.
我够大了
I'm old enough.
除了这个 还能做很多别的
I'm old enough for a lot of things.
在纽约那会 我们整晚刷夜
In New York, we stay up all night,
然后看着太阳爬上仓库屋顶
watch the sun come up over the warehouses.
在那儿 总是有新鲜事可做
There's always something to do.
明天我就得回去了
I have to go back tomorrow.
- 这么快 - 真想留下来
- So soon. - Wish I could stay.
如今 跳舞的人 都不需要服装和背景了
Dancers don't need costumes or scenery anymore.
我都能想象 自己不穿衣服跳舞的样子
I can imagine dancing completely naked.
你读过D.H.劳伦斯的书吗？
Have you read D.H. Lawrence?
- 呃… - 他的书都被禁了
- Well... - His books were banned.
那些文字 读起来 就像做爱
The words are like making love.
在舞团 大家必须互相信任
In our company, we have to trust each other.
性 就是条件之一
Sex is a part of it.
知道嘛 很多跳舞的都是女同
You know, a lot of the dancers are lesbians.
有一个女人 就想跟我睡
There was one woman who wanted to sleep with me.
- 你听了会不高兴吗？ - 关于哪部分？
- Does that upset you? - Which part?
就是有人想和我睡那部分
Somebody wanting to sleep with me.
你很性感
You're a desirable woman.
我想 他们很多人都会想和你睡吧
I would think most of them would want to sleep with you.
咱们回去吧
Let's go back to the house.
或者到哪开间房
Or we could get a room somewhere.
- 你可以脱下夹克… - 这样似乎不好 黛西
- We could lay down your jacket. - I don't know, Daisy.
也不是说我不想还是怎么的 我只是怕 会让你失望
It's not that I wouldn't like to or anything. I think I'll just disappoint you.
本杰明 我和更老的人都在一起过
Oh, Benjamin, I've been with older men.
明早你就要回纽约了
You're going back to New York in the morning.
你该和朋友在一起
You should be with your friends.
- 你只能年轻一次 - 我够大了
- You're only young once. - Oh, I'm old enough.
黛西 就是 今晚不行
Daisy, just not tonight, is all.
我们可以去听听音乐
We could go hear some music.
我们的生命 因为各种各样的机遇 而变得更有意义
Our lives are defined by opportunities.
甚至那些我们错过的
Even the ones we miss.
你看起来 如此英俊 与众不同
You look so handsome and so distinguished.
据说飓风不会过来 刚好从我们这块刮过去
They're saying the hurricane's gonna miss us, blow right on by.
- 太好了 - 我在毯子下面和妈妈一起躺着
- Oh, that's great. - I'll stay under the blankets with Mother.
她什么也没说…本杰明你在吗？
She says nothing... Benjamin?
“我的生命…
"Things were becoming different..."
又有了不一样的变化
... for me.
我的头发 越来越黑 像野草一样生长
My hair had very little gray and grew like weeds.
我的嗅觉更加灵敏 听觉 也加更敏锐
My sense of smell was keener. My hearing, more acute.
我走得更快更远
I could walk further and faster.
别人都在变老 而我 却独自一人 越来越年轻
While everybody else was aging, I was getting younger, all alone.
进来吧
Come in.
本杰明
Benjamin.
- 还记得我吗？ - 当然了 巴顿先生
- Do you remember me? - Well, sure I do, Mr. Button.
- 你这是怎么了？ - 该死的脚 感染了 那个…
- What happened to you? - Darn foot. Got infected, so...
欢迎回家 朋友
Welcome home, my friend.
你还是喜欢把威士忌 和别的酒混起来喝啊
I see you're still drinking your Sazerac with whiskey.
呵 习惯这东西
Creature of habit.
你还常去波旁大道那边的工厂吗？
You still visiting the house on Bourbon Street?
很久没去了
Not for a long time.
说来有趣
Interesting times, though.
我们一开始每天做四万个纽扣 到后来一天50万
We went from making 40,000 to nearly half a million buttons a day.
厂里的工人多了十倍
We employed 10 times the number of people.
我们没日没夜地工作
We were operating around the clock.
说来惭愧
Damn shame.
战争让纽扣生意更红火了
The war has been kind to the button industry.
知道嘛
You know,
我病了 不知道还能活多久
I'm sick. I don't know how much longer I have.
- 您也别太难过了 巴顿先生 - 别这么说…
- I'm sorry to hear that, Mr. Button. - No...
我没什么朋友 一直都是独来独往
I don't have any people. I keep to myself.
但愿你不要介意 不过 如果有可能
I hope you don't mind, but, whenever possible,
我希望你可以多陪陪我
I'd enjoy your company.
如果力所能及 我当然会的
I'll certainly do what I can.
本杰明 你懂纽扣生意吗？
Benjamin, do you know anything about buttons?
到现在 巴顿纽扣厂已经 在家族中传承了124年了
Now, Button's Buttons has been in our family for 124 years.
我的祖父是个裁缝 只在里士满开了间小裁缝铺
My grandfather was a tailor, and he had a small shop in Richmond.
内战过后 他搬到了新奥尔良
After the Civil War, he moved to New Orleans,
在那儿 我父亲奋发图强 开始经营自己的纽扣生意
where my father had the wisdom to make our own buttons.
于是 在他的大力改革下 小裁缝铺成长到了今天这样的规模
So, with his help, the tailor shop grew to this.
如今 我却连衣服都不会自己缝了
And today, I can't sew a stitch.
这故事真的很有意思
That's very, very interesting.
很显然 您自己干得也不错嘛
You sure have done well for yourself.
那我能帮上什么忙呢 巴顿先生？
So, what can I do for you, Mr. Button?
本杰明 你是我儿子
Benjamin? You're my son.
抱歉 我以前从没提起过
I'm so sorry I never told you before.
你是大战结束那晚出生的
You were born the night the Great War ended.
你母亲难产而死
Your mother died giving birth to you.
我以为你是怪物
I thought you were a monster.
我向你母亲保证过 保证你会平平安安
I promised your mother I'd make sure you were safe.
对不起 我不该抛弃你
I should never have abandoned you.
我母亲？
My mother?
庞恰特雷恩湖边的避暑别墅
At the summer house on Lake Pontchartrain.
我小时候 总喜欢比大家早起
When I was a boy, I'd love to wake up before anyone else,
然后跑到湖边 迎接新一天的开始
run down to that lake and watch the day begin.
那时候 我觉得自己 好像是这世上唯一一个活人
It was as if I was the only one alive.
第一眼看到她 我就爱上她了
I fell in love the first time I saw her.
你母亲叫卡洛琳・墨菲
Your mother's name was Caroline Murphy.
她在你爷爷的厨房里干活
She worked in your grandfather's kitchen.
她是都柏林人
She's from Dublin.
1903年 她和她的兄弟姐妹 就到美国来谋生了
In 1903, Caroline and all her brothers and sisters came to live here,
就住在新奥尔良
in New Orleans.
我常常找借口下厨房
I'd find excuses to go down to that kitchen
就为了看她一眼
just so I could look at her.
1918年4月25号 那天 是我一生中最快乐的时光
April 25th, 1918. Happiest day of my life.
那天 我迎娶了你母亲
The day I married your mother.
你为什么不早点告诉我？
Why didn't you just tell me?
我准备把遗产都留给你
I plan on leaving everything I have to you.
- 我该走了 - 去哪？
- I have to go. - Where?
回家
Home.
他怎么想的 嗯？
And what does he think, anyway?
他以为自己这么冒出来
He thinks he can just show up
然后就没事了？
and everything's supposed to be fine and dandy.
然后大家就能做朋友了？
Everybody's just supposed to be friends.
要我说 这事我跟他没完
Well, he got another thing coming, that's for sure.
老天有眼 我跟他没完！
God be my witness, he got another thing coming.
他丢掉你那晚 只留了18块钱
He left us $18 that night you was found.
18张皱巴巴的票子！
Eighteen ratty dollars
- 还有一块脏兮兮的尿布 - 晚安了 妈
- and a filthy diaper. - Good night, Mama.
晚安 宝贝儿
Good night, baby.
我有没有跟你说过 我被闪电击中过七次？
Did I ever tell you I was struck by lightning seven times?
有一次 我就那么好好得遛着狗
Once, I was walking my dog down the road.
现在我瞎了一只眼 几乎听不见
I'm blind in the one eye, can't hardly hear,
还无缘无故抽搐发抖 老是忘东西
get twitches and shakes out of nowhere, always losing my line of thought.
但你知道嘛？
But you know what?
老天爷总是不断地提醒我 让我知道自己还活着 有多幸运
God keeps reminding me I'm lucky to be alive.
暴风雨快来了
Storm's coming.
可以为您效劳吗？ 楼上 第一间卧室
May I help you, sir? Up the stairs, first bedroom.
谢谢
Thank you.
醒醒
Wake up.
我来帮你穿上衣服
Let's get you dressed.
对 就这样
Now that's something.
谢谢
Thank you.
不顺心的时候 你可以像疯狗那样发狂
You can be mad as a mad dog at the way things went.
你可以破口大骂 诅咒命运
You can swear and curse the Fates.
但到头来
But when it comes to the end,
还是得放手
you have to let go.
这葬礼很体面
Well, it sure is a beautiful service.
他会葬在你母亲旁边
He'll be buried right next to your mother.
您就是我母亲
You're my mother.
我的孩子
My baby.
我以前还从没来过纽约
Now, I'd never seen New York.
- 打扰下 我是黛西的朋友 - 这边
- Excuse me, I'm a friend of Daisy's. - Right this way.
- 黛西有人找 黛西！ - 来了！
- Daisy has company. Daisy! Daisy! - Yes!
- 我们要放衣服 - 是谁找我呀？
- We need the wardrobe. - Is somebody looking for me?
- 本杰明 - 嗨
- Benjamin. - Hi.
- 你来这做什么？ - 我觉得应该来看看你
- What are you doing here? - Thought I'd come visit.
要是可以 约你出去转转
Spend some time with you, if I could.
真希望你事先给我个电话 这样我都没法准备
Oh, well, I wish you would've called. You took me by surprise.
- 要是不喜欢就扔了吧 - 哪里 谢了 花很好看
- You can just throw them out. - No. Thank you, they're lovely.
我从头到尾都在看你 你真是…太迷人了
I couldn't take my eyes off of you. I thought you were mesmerizing.
谢谢 谢谢你这么说
Thank you. That's very kind of you to say.
我得去换身衣服了 我们几个要去聚会下
I better get changed. A group of us are going to a party.
- 你来吗？ - 听人说有家餐馆不错
- Would you want to come? - Someone told me about a restaurant
你应该也会喜欢
I thought you might enjoy.
我定了位 算是以防万一
I made a reservation, just in case.
不过我们跳完舞之后都会聚聚…
Just, all the dancers go out after the show. You're...
你来我们会很欢迎的 我去换衣服 好吗？
You're welcome to come with us. I'll get changed. All right?
她还给俄罗斯芭蕾舞团排过舞
She choreographs for the Ballets Russes.
太神了
She's divine.
你真美
You were breathtaking.
小甜心
Sweetie.
这是大卫 他也是舞团的
This is David. He dances with the company.
- 这是本杰明 - 谁？
- This is Benjamin. - Who?
- 我跟你说起过他的 - 哦 是你啊 近来可好啊
- I told you about him. - Oh, yeah. How you doing?
- 我去给你拿杯喝的 - 嗯 谢了
- I'll go get you a drink. - All right. Thanks.
这么说 你是她奶奶的朋友？
So, you were a friend of her grandmother's?
还是就那一类的？
Or something like that?
差不多吧
Something like that.
嘿 失陪
Hey, excuse me.
来吧
Come on.
嘿！
Hey!
我真不知道你会来
Now, I had no idea you were coming.
天啊 本杰明
Lord, Benjamin.
你想要我怎样呢？ 难道要我丢下这一切 跟你走吗？
What did you expect? What, you want me to drop everything?
这可是我的人生
Now, this is my life.
宝贝儿 去市中心不？
Babe! You going downtown?
来吧 你也会玩得很开心的
Come on. You'll have a good time.
那儿有很多音乐家和有趣的人
There's lots of musicians, interesting people.
真的不用了 都是我不好
You don't have to do that. This is my fault.
我是该先打个电话
I should've called.
我本以为我突然过来
I thought I'd come here
会给你一个大惊喜
and sweep you off your feet or something.
- 黛西 快来吧 出发了！ - 马上到
- Daisy! Come on! Let's go. - Be right there.
他看来还不错
Seems nice.
你爱他吗？
Do you love him?
应该吧
I think so.
真替你高兴
I'm happy for you.
那老家见吧
Maybe I'll see you at home.
好吧
Okay.
我很喜欢你的演出！
I enjoyed the show!
他来 是想告诉我 他父亲死了
He came to tell me his father had died.
- 你也猜不到啊 - 我那时才23岁 我…只是不在乎这些
- You couldn't have known. - I was 23. I... I just didn't care.
那你后来呢？
What did you do next?
有些照片 我记得 就放在包的前袋里
Some photographs, I think, in the front of my bag.
我那会还挺了不得
I was as good a dancer as I was ever gonna be.
有那么五年 我…
For five years, I...
在世界各地表演
I danced everywhere.
伦敦 维也纳 布拉格
London, Vienna, Prague.
我从没见过这些照片
I've never seen these.
妈
Mom.
你从来没提你跳舞的事
You never talked about your dancing.
我还是头一个
Well, I was the only American
受邀 和大剧院舞团共舞的美国人 （Bolshoi：俄国著名芭蕾舞团）
to be invited to dance with the Bolshoi, sugar.
那真是太棒了
It was glorious.
但我从没忘记本杰明
But Benjamin was never far from my thoughts.
有时候 我会不自觉地说…
And I'd find myself saying...
晚安 本杰明
Good night, Benjamin.
- “晚安 黛西” - 他也这么说？
- "Good night, Daisy." - He said that?
“生活并没有那么复杂
"Life wasn't all that complicated.
要是你喜欢 大可以说我是在探索生命”
"If you want, you might say I was looking for something."
本杰明 拉・图尔诺夫人刚刚过世了
Benjamin? Mrs. La Tourneau just passed.
- 本杰明・巴顿先生的信 - 我就是
- Letter for Mr. Benjamin Button? - That'd be me.
谢谢
Thank you.
我找黛西・富勒小姐
Miss Daisy Fuller.
- 稍等 请先坐一会 - 好的
- Just a minute. Please have a seat. - Sure.
有时候 我们的人生轨道 会与别人的交错 只是不自知罢了
Sometimes we're on a collision course and we just don't know it.
无论是意外 还是天意 我们都无力改变
Whether it's by accident or by design, there's not a thing we can do about it.
巴黎 一名女子正要出门购物
A woman in Paris was on her way to go shopping.
却发现忘带外套 于是回家去取
But she had forgotten her coat, went back to get it.
她拿起外套 电话铃响
When she had gotten her coat, the phone had rung.
她接起电话 聊了一会
So she had stopped to answer it and talked for a couple of minutes.
与此同时
While the woman was on the phone,
黛西正为一场巴黎歌剧院的演出彩排
Daisy was rehearsing for a performance at the Paris Opera House.
不久 女子聊完 挂了电话
And while she was rehearsing, the woman, off the phone now,
下楼去招出租车
had gone outside to get a taxi.
另一边 出租车司机 刚刚送完一位客人
Now, a taxi driver had dropped off a fare earlier,
便停了车 去买咖啡
and had stopped to get a cup of coffee.
而黛西还在继续排练
And all the while, Daisy was rehearsing.
那位送完了客人
And this cab driver, who dropped off the earlier fare
便去买咖啡的司机
and had stopped to get the cup of coffee,
正巧接了要去购物的那位女子
he picked up the lady who was going shopping
而那位女子 因为一番延误 刚错过了之前的车
and had missed getting the earlier cab.
车子中途停了一下 因为有人横穿马路
The taxi had to stop for a man crossing the street,
这位男子那天比平时晚起了五分钟
who had left for work five minutes later than he normally did
因为他忘了定闹钟
because he forgot to set his alarm.
那个没定闹钟 早上迟到的人 横穿马路的时候
While that man, late for work, was crossing the street,
黛西已经排练结束 开始冲澡
Daisy had finished rehearsing and was taking a shower.
她在洗澡的时候
And while Daisy was showering,
出租车停在一家糖果店门口 等女客人去取包裹
the taxi was waiting outside a boutique for the woman to pick up a package
可包裹还没备好
which hadn't been wrapped yet,
因为打包的女孩
because the girl who was supposed to wrap it
昨晚刚刚与男友分手 太过伤心而忘了打包
had broken up with her boyfriend the night before and forgot.
包裹打好之后 女子回到车上
When the package was wrapped, the woman, who was back in the cab,
又被一辆货车挡住了去路
was blocked by a delivery truck.
与此同时 黛西换上了衣服
All the while, Daisy was getting dressed.
货车开走之后 出租才重新上路
The delivery truck pulled away, and the taxi was able to move
而黛西最后一个才穿好衣服
while Daisy, the last to be dressed,
又等了一会断了鞋带的朋友
waited for one of her friends who had broken a shoelace.
出租在路灯处停下时
While the taxi was stopped, waiting for a traffic light,
黛西和她朋友正从剧场后门出来
Daisy and her friend came out the back of the theater.
如果有一件事 有一点点不一样
And if only one thing had happened differently,
如果那鞋带没断
if that shoelace hadn't broken
如果那货车早一点儿开走
or that delivery truck had moved moments earlier
或者包裹早早备好
or that package had been wrapped and ready
因为男孩没和女孩分手
because the girl hadn't broken up with her boyfriend,
又或者那男子定了闹钟 和平时一样起床
or that man had set his alarm and got up five minutes earlier
再或者司机没有停车喝咖啡
or that taxi driver hadn't stopped for a cup of coffee
而那女子也带了外套 上了之前的出租
or that woman had remembered her coat and got into an earlier cab,
那么 黛西和她朋友 就会平平安安地穿过马路
Daisy and her friend would have crossed the street
那出租也只是和她们擦身而过
and the taxi would have driven by.
但是 生活没有如果
But, life being what it is,
只有一连串互相交错的意外
a series of intersecting lives and incidents
无人能够控制
out of anyone's control,
那辆出租没有和她们擦身而过
that taxi did not go by,
而就在那时 司机分了一下神
and that driver was momentarily distracted.
黛西！
Daisy!
车子撞倒了黛西
And that taxi hit Daisy.
黛西！来人啊！
Daisy! Help!
她的腿 就被撞断了
And her leg was crushed.
黛西？
Daisy?
- 谁让你来的？ - 你朋友写信给我
- Who told you? - Your friend wired me.
你这么大老远来看我 真是好心
Very kind of you to come all this way to see that I was all right.
换了是你 也会这么做的
You'd do the same for me.
我的天
My God.
瞧瞧你 你太完美了
Look at you. You're perfect.
真希望你没来这 我不想你看到我这样子
I wish you hadn't come here. I don't want you to see me like this.
她的腿 断成了五段
Her leg had been broken in five places.
如果治疗得当 假以时日 她或许还能重新走路
And with therapy and time, she might walk again.
但不可能再跳舞了
But she'd never dance.
我带你回家
I'm gonna take you home with me.
- 我愿意照顾你 - 我不回新奥尔良
- I want to look after you. - I'm not going back to New Orleans.
那我就留在巴黎陪你
Then I'll stay here in Paris.
你还不明白吗？我不用你可怜我！
Don't you understand? I don't want your help.
我现在是很难过 可也不用你陪
I know I'm feeling sorry for myself, but I don't want to be with you.
在纽约那会就想告诉你了 可你就是不听
Tried to tell you that in New York. You don't listen.
你或许会改变主意
You might change your mind.
你也不是小孩子了 本杰明
We are not little children anymore, Benjamin.
拜托 从我的生命里消失吧
Just stay out of my life.
我真的是太狠心了
I was awfully cruel.
他一定不明白 我只是不想让他看我那副样子
He didn't understand. I couldn't have him see me like that.
“我没有马上离开
"I didn't leave right away.
而是在巴黎逗留了一阵子 暗中照看她”
"I stayed in Paris for a while to look out for her."
我一点也不知道
I never knew that.
哦 亲爱的 能帮我叫下护士吗？
Oh, darling, could you get the nurse?
我又重新学会走路
I taught myself to walk again.
又坐火车去卢尔德（法国西南部小城）
I took the train to Lourdes.
我看看 很正常 脉搏舒缓下来了
Let's take a look. That's normal. Pulse rate is slowing.
稍后可能会呼吸困难一会
She is gonna struggle to breathe.
- 你在这没事吧？ - 嗯
- Will you be all right? - Yeah.
我接着读 他说“我回到家” 这里有很多页被撕掉了
All right, he says, "I went back home." And then there's a lot of pages torn out.
“我聆听着房子的低语” 我读过这段了
"I listened to the sound of the house." I read that already.
他…
He...
他把什么东西溅到纸上 这段看不清了 妈
He spilt something on it, so it's hard to read, Mom.
好像是关于帆船的 您知道他在说什么吗？
Something about sailing, does that make sense?
我用父亲留在湖边别墅的帆船 学会了驾驶
I learned to sail an old boat of my father's from the lake house.
说老实话
I can't lie.
我也确实很享受 与一两位女子共度的时光
I did enjoy the company of a woman or two.
也许是三个吧
Or maybe three.
何必这么烦呢 山姆 反正明天还是要去一趟的
Don't know why you bother, Sam, just gonna be there again tomorrow.
妈妈
Mama.
1962年春天
And in the spring of 1962,
她回来了
she came back.
- 想知道我去了哪儿吗？ - 不想
- You want to know where I've been? - No.
你怎么连封信也不写？ 就那么人间蒸发了一样
How come you didn't write or nothing? Just disappearing like that.
我只是去处理了一下私事
It was something I needed to do for myself.
我也从没觉得你自私
Yeah, well, I never took you to be the selfish type.
但愿如此
I sure hope I'm not wrong.
我一般看人不会看走眼的
I'm usually not wrong about people.
- 晚安 妈妈 - 晚安 宝贝儿
- Good night, Mama. - Good night, baby.
你俩好好玩吧
Y'all have fun.
- 你说到现在 还没哪句话多过两个字呢 - 我只是不想破坏气氛
- You haven't said two words. - I don't want to ruin it.
- 和我睡吧 - 绝对地
- Sleep with me? - Absolutely.
我邀她与我出游
I asked her to come away with me.
我们沿着佛罗里达群岛 一路乘帆驶进海湾
We sailed into the Gulf along the Florida Keys.
真高兴我不是26岁那年和你在一起
I am so glad we didn't find one another when I was 26.
- 这话怎么说？ - 我那会太嫩了
- Why do you say that? - I was so young.
你又太老
And you were so old.
现在这样 才最自然
It happened when it was supposed to happen.
和你在一起的每分每秒 我都会珍惜
I will enjoy each and every moment I have with you.
我跟你打赌 我在这能比你坚持更久
I bet I can stay out here longer than you.
那我赌你撑不了
I bet you can't.
你脸上几乎没有皱纹
Barely a line or a crease.
而我 每天都会多长出几条 不公平
Every day I have more wrinkles. It's not fair.
我喜欢你的皱纹 每一条都爱
I love your wrinkles. Both of them.
越活越年轻是种什么感觉？
What's it like growing younger?
还真是很难形容 我自己又没法看到全部变化
I can't really say. I'm always looking out my own eyes.
我要是成了黄脸婆 你还会爱我吗？
Will you still love me when my skin grows old and saggy?
等我老到脸上长满青春痘 老到尿床
Will you still love me when I have acne? When I wet the bed?
老到连楼梯下有什么都怕 你还会爱我吗？
When I'm afraid of what's under the stairs?
怎么了？
What?
- 你在想什么？ - 我在想 为什么世上没有永恒呢
- What are you thinking? - Well, I was thinking how nothing lasts.
多可惜
And what a shame that is.
有些事情 是永恒的
Some things last.
- 晚安 黛西 - 晚安 本杰明
- Good night, Daisy. - Good night, Benjamin.
妈？
Mom?
- 你什么时候认识爸爸的？ - 在那之后
- When did you meet Dad? - Some time after that.
- 你跟他说过这个本杰明的事吗？ - 亲爱的 他知道得不少
- Did you tell him about this Benjamin? - He knew enough, darling.
妈？
Mama?
奎尼？
Queenie?
是谁啊？
Hello?
哦 嗨 卡特夫人 大家都上哪去了？
Oh, hi, Mrs. Carter, it's Benjamin. Where is everybody?
哦 本杰明 奎尼去世了 节哀啊
Oh, Benjamin. Queenie died. I'm so sorry.
你失去亲人 我也很难过 她是个好女人
I'm so sorry for your loss. She was a great woman.
我们深表哀悼
Our deepest condolences.
她葬在她的挚爱 韦瑟斯身边
We buried her beside her beloved Mr. Weathers.
为了过上我们自己的生活
And so we might have memories of our own,
我卖了父亲的房子
we sold my father's house on Esplanade.
亲爱的 这老房子真是太棒了！
It is a wonderful old place, darling.
我想我们生活在这里会很开心
I think we are going to be so happy here.
哦 好长的家族史啊
Oh, what a long family history you have.
和房子的历史一样长
They come with the house.
- 上来吧 - 你一定得看看主卧室
- Come on. - You have to see the master suite.
我们买了一套二联式的小公寓
We bought ourselves a duplex.
我爱死那房子了
I loved that house.
有木柴的味道
It smelled like firewood.
别…别停下 亲爱的
Don't... Don't stop, darling.
“那是我生命中最快乐的时光”
"It was one of the happiest times of my life."
我们半件家具也没有
We didn't have a stick of furniture.
在起居室里野餐
We would have picnics in the living room.
想什么时候吃饭就什么时候吃 只要愿意 就通宵不睡
We ate when we felt like it. Stayed up all night when we wanted.
我们发誓 一定不过循规蹈矩的生活
We vowed never to fall into routine,
绝不按时上床 起床
to go to bed or wake up at the same time.
我们就在床垫上过活
We lived on that mattress.
我们的邻居 凡・丹夫人 是个理疗师
Our neighbor, a Mrs. Van Dam, was a physical therapist.
离家四个街区 就有个公共泳池
We lived four blocks from a public pool.
也许 你能多跳几年舞
You know, you might've got a few more years out of it,
可你的事业太与众不同
but you chose to do something so special and unique
只有几年的黄金时间可以发展
that there was only a short window of time you could do it.
就算没发生意外
So, even if nothing ever happened,
你现在还是会回来 在这
you'd still be right here where you are now.
我只是不喜欢变老
I just don't like getting old.
这里的水消毒过头了 （泳池用氯气消毒 氯气有强刺激性）
They put too much chlorine in here.
我保证 以后再也不会自怨自艾了
I promise you I'll never lose myself to self-pity again.
那时候 我知道
And I think right there and then
她懂了 没人是永远完美无瑕的
she realized none of us is perfect forever.
她的内心 终于平静了
She found peace.
她办了间舞蹈室 教小女孩跳舞
She opened a studio and taught young girls how to dance.
足尖点地
And tendu.
跳回来 点地 点地 点地 好极了！
Come back the other way. And spot, spot, spot. Excellent.
- 晚安 黛西老师 - 晚安
- Good night, Miss Daisy. - Good night.
你看起来真美
You certainly are beautiful to watch.
舞蹈好不好就看身线
Dancing's all about the line.
身体的曲线
The line of your body.
早晚 身线都有不好的一天 之后 就一去不复返了
Sooner or later, you lose that line, and you never get it back.
我算了下 你是1918年出生的 今年也49了
I figure, you were born in 1918, 49 years ago.
我43
I'm 43.
差不多算是同龄
We are almost the same age.
- 我们在人生的中点相遇 - 总算是遇上了
- We're meeting in the middle. - We finally caught up with each other.
等下
Wait.
我想记着我们现在的样子
I want to remember us just as we are now.
我有了
I'm pregnant.
知道嘛 我敢打赌 那护士说漏过嘴 是男孩
You know, I swear the nurse slipped and said it was a boy.
可我觉得是女孩
But I think it's a girl.
- 我知道你担心 - 我也没藏着掖着
- I know you're afraid. - I'm not hiding it.
好吧
Okay.
- 你最担心什么？ - 孩子像我
- What's your worst fear? - Baby born like me.
那我更爱他还来不及呢
Then I will love it all the more.
这么说吧 我这样越活越小 怎么能当好一个父亲？
Okay. How can I be a father when I'm heading in the other direction?
对孩子来说也不公平 我不想变成累赘
It's not fair to a child. I don't want to be anybody's burden.
甜心 到头来 我们都会重新用上尿布
Sugar, we all end up in diapers.
我会想办法 让一切都顺利
I am gonna make this work.
我想要这孩子 我想和你一起 把他养育成人
I want this, and I want it with you.
你想要什么 我就尽量给你 无论有多难
I want you to have everything you want, all of it.
只是现在 我还没想好 我这样子 怎么才能不影响到孩子
I'm just not sure how to reconcile this.
你会跟一个盲人说 他不能有孩子吗？
Would you tell a blind man he couldn't have children?
打包好了
Here you go.
你是孩子的父亲 能当多久当多久
You'll be a father for as long as you can.
我知道最后会是什么结局 我也准备好面对了
I know the consequences. I've accepted that.
为了爱你 我可以不惜一切
Loving you is worth everything to me.
我要嘘嘘去
I have to go pee.
有史以来 横渡英吉利海峡 最年长的妇女
The oldest woman to ever swim the English Channel
今日游抵加来…
arrived here today in Calais...
- 不用找了 - 全程花去34小时
- Keep it. - ... having made the swim in 34 hours,
22分钟 14秒
22 minutes and 14 seconds.
现年68岁的伊丽莎白・艾伯特 于格林尼治时间5:38抵岸
The 68-year-old Elizabeth Abbott arrived at 5:38 Greenwich mean time,
虽然精疲力竭 但还是笑逐颜开
exhausted but happy.
艾伯特女士 能用几句话来概括 形容下您的此次壮举吗？
Miss Abbott, how would you sum up, in words, this achievement?
那我得说…
I suppose...
凡事皆有可能
Anything's possible.
- 够了吗？ - 嗯 非常感谢
- All right? - Yes. Thank you.
- 可以走了吗？ - 真谢谢你
- You ready? - Thank you very much.
谢谢大家
Thank you. Thank you all.
- 嗯 - 你们真好
- Yeah. - You're very kind.
春天里的某一天 寻常的一天…
In the spring, on a day like any other...
我出门去 一小时就回来！
I'll be back in an hour!
亲爱的？
Honey?
快叫救护车！
Go and call an ambulance!
快生了
The baby's coming.
接线员 我找救护车
Operator, I need an ambulance.
- 快生了！ - 拿破仑路2714号
- The baby's coming! - 2714 Napoleon.
就这样 注意呼吸
There you go. Keep breathing.
深呼吸 用力！
Deep breaths. Push.
就这样
There we go.
母女平安 孩子很健康
Everyone's fine. She's a perfectly healthy baby girl.
亲爱的？
Honey?
她生下了一个5磅4盎司重的女孩 （约6斤3两）
She gave birth to a five pound, four ounce baby girl.
你数过脚趾了吗？
Did you count the toes?
她可真漂亮
She's perfect.
“我们用我母亲的名字 给她取名 卡罗琳”
"And we named her for my mother, Caroline."
这个叫本杰明的 是我父亲？
This Benjamin was my father?
你就这么告诉我真相？
And this is how you tell me?
我走开一会
Excuse me.
一场特大飓风所需具备的条件 都已成形
... because all the ingredients are there for a major storm,
本次飓风甚至可能达到第5级 （约相当于16级台风）
possibly even up to a Category 5.
嘿 我知道你不好受 可不能在这吸烟
Hey, I know it's hard. You can't smoke in here.
目前还不知其登陆地点
Nobody can tell you exactly where it's gonna hit,
但我们会尽快查阅已有资料
but we have to go with the guidance that we have,
重新整理 并为大家 提供相应的防台措施
incorporate that information and then pass it along to you.
“医生说得没错 你慢慢长大 正常 健康”
"You grew as the doctor had promised, normal and healthy."
你该给她找个能胜任的父亲
You're gonna have to find a real father for her.
你说什么呀
What are you talking about?
得有人陪着她长大
She's gonna need someone to grow old with.
她会学着接受这一切的 再说 她爱你
She'll learn to accept whatever happens. She loves you.
亲爱的 她需要的是父亲 不是玩伴
Honey, she needs a father, not a playmate.
- 是我的问题吗？ - 当然不是
- Is it me? - Of course not.
- 是不是我变老了 惹你嫌了？ - 当然不是
- Is my age beginning to bother you? - Of course not.
- 你是不是就这个意思？ - 你没法把我们两个一起养
- Is that what you're telling me? - You can't raise the both of us.
今天是你的第一次生日 我们为你办了场生日聚会
It was your first birthday. We had a party for you.
屋子里全是小朋友
The house was filled with children.
- 近来如何啊？ - 嘿 老兄
- How are you? - Hey, man.
一眨眼的功夫 他们就该上高中 开始约会了
Before you turn around, they'll be in high school, dating.
我卖了庞恰特雷恩湖边的避暑别墅
I sold the summer house on Lake Pontchartrain,
卖了巴顿纽扣厂
I sold Button's Buttons,
卖了父亲的帆船 把钱全都存进了银行
I sold my father's sailboat, put it all into a savings account.
这样你和你妈妈或许能过上好日子
And so that you and your mother might have a life,
趁你还不记得我 我得早日离开
I left, before you could ever remember me.
“离开的时候 我只带走了身上穿的衣服”
"I left with just the clothes on my back."
我不想再念了 您能不能直接告诉我 他去哪了？
I don't want to read this now. Can you just tell me where he went?
我也不知道
I don't really know.
这是寄给我的 1970年 我才两岁 “生日快乐”
It's for me. 1970. I was two. "Happy Birthday."
“我希望 可以在你临睡前 吻你”
"I wish I could have kissed you good night."
都是寄给我的
They're all for me.
五岁 “我希望 可以领着你 上第一天学”
Five. "I wish I could have taken you to your first day of school."
六岁 “我希望 可以在你身边 教你钢琴”
Six. "I wish I could have been there to teach you to play piano."
1981年 13岁
1981, 13.
“我希望 可以告诉你 别去追那帮楞头小子”
"I wish I could have told you not to chase some boy.
“我希望 你伤心的时候 有我安慰”
"I wish I could have held you when you had a broken heart.
“我希望 我可以当你爸爸 再没有什么 比这更让我梦绕”
"I wish I could have been your father. Nothing I ever did will replace that."
我猜他去过印度
I guess he went to India.
“只要是有意义的事 再晚去做还有意义的”
"For what it's worth, it's never too late,
- “不过如果是我说 该说再‘早’…” - 再‘早’去做都是有意义的
- "or, in my case, too early..." - ... or, in my case, too early,
做你想做的人
to be whoever you want to be.
这件事 没有时间的限制 只要愿意 什么时候都可以开始
There's no time limit. Start whenever you want.
你能从现在开始改变 也可以一成不变 这件事 没有规矩可言
You can change or stay the same. There are no rules to this thing.
你能活出最精彩的自己 也可能搞得一团糟
We can make the best or the worst of it.
我希望 你能活出最精彩的自己
And I hope you make the best of it.
我希望 你能见识到令你惊奇的事物
I hope you see things that startle you.
我希望 你能体验未曾体验过的情感
I hope you feel things you never felt before.
我希望 你能遇见一些想法不同的人
I hope you meet people with a different point of view.
我希望 你为你自己的人生感到骄傲
I hope you live a life you're proud of.
如果你发现自己还没有做到 我希望 你有勇气
And if you find that you're not, I hope you have the strength
- 重头再来 - “重头再来”
- to start all over again. - "...start all over again."
他离开我们很久
He had been gone a long time.
下周四见了
I'll see you next Thursday.
- 晚安 黛西老师 - 晚安 小甜心
- Good night, Miss Daisy. - Oh, good night, sweetheart.
抱歉 我们要关门了
I'm sorry, we're closing.
有什么需要帮忙的吗
Can I help you?
您是来接孩子吗？
Are you here to pick somebody up?
你为什么要回来？
Why did you come back?
妈？
Mom?
可以走了吧？
You ready yet?
妈 怎么了？
Mom, what's wrong?
只是刚刚听说一个朋友的噩耗
I was just hearing a very sad story about a mutual friend
我都很久没见过他了
who I hadn't seen for a very long time.
卡罗琳 这是本杰明
Caroline, this is Benjamin.
其实你小时候就认识他了
You knew him when you were just a baby.
- 嗨 - 嗨
- Hi. - Hi.
嘿
Hey.
- 哦 抱歉 我还以为你完事了 - 这位是我家的世交
- Oh, I'm sorry, I thought you were done. - Oh, this is a friend of my family's.
本杰明・巴顿 这是我丈夫 罗伯特
Benjamin Button, this is my husband, Robert.
- 你好 - 幸会
- How do you do? - A pleasure.
嗯 很高兴认识你
Well, it was very nice to meet you.
- 我们就在车上等了 亲爱的 - 嗯 好
- We'll be in the car, darling. - All right.
拜
Bye.
我去关门
I'm just locking up.
哇
Wow.
她可真美 像她母亲
She's beautiful. Like her mother.
- 她跳舞吗？ - 跳得不是很好
- Does she dance? - Not very well.
估计是遗传我的吧
I guess that'd be from my side of things.
她是个好姑娘
She's a dear, sweet girl.
只是有点迷惘 不过说回来 谁12岁的时候不是呢
She seems a little lost. But then, who isn't at 12?
她总是让我想起…你
A lot of her reminds me of you.
我丈夫是个鳏夫 那个…过去是
My husband, he's a widower, or was... Was a widower.
他是个大好人 爱冒险 很阳光
He's an incredibly kind, just bright, adventurous man.
- 他也是个好父亲 - 真好
- He's been a terrific father. - Good.
- 你看起来 又年轻了好多 - 只是外表
- You are so much younger. - Only on the outside.
你说得对
You were right.
我没法同时养你们两个人
I couldn't have been raising both of you.
我不够坚强
I'm not that strong.
那你住哪？
So, where are you staying?
接下来准备干什么？
What are you gonna do?
我住在庞恰特雷恩旅店
I'm staying at the Pontchartrain Hotel on the Avenue.
也不知道接着该干什么
I don't know what I'm gonna do.
不过…
But...
他们在等我
They're waiting.
我还记得 他就是？
I remember that. That was him?
飓风转向了
The hurricane has changed directions.
不久就登陆
It's going to make landfall sometime soon.
- 我该做些什么？ - 正在组织撤离人员
- Am I supposed to do something? - Arrangements are being made
不过走不走还是你自己说了算
to move people, but it's up to you.
不了 我们留着
No. No, we're... We're staying.
要是情况有变 我会及时通知你
I'll let you know if anything changes.
“那晚 我正坐着 奇怪自己为什么要回来”
"That night, while I was sitting and wondering why I came back at all,
“传来了敲门声”
"there was a knock at the door."
进来吧
Come in.
你过得好吗？
Are you all right?
对不起 我都不知道 自己来这是要干嘛
I'm sorry, I don't know what I'm doing here.
没什么是永恒的
Nothing lasts.
我爱你 从没变过
I have never stopped loving you.
哦 别 本杰明 我太老了
Oh, but, Benjamin, I'm an old woman now.
有些事 你永远都不会忘记
Some things you never forget.
很少有人知道
... so few people even know
您过去还蹲过监狱
that you were ever in jail in the first place.
告诉您吧 我也觉得不爽
I'll tell you, I am sick about it, too,
因为 拜托 他们就算不给您颁个
because, please, if they're not gonna give you an award
“年度人物”之类的大奖 至少
like "Man of the Year," at least what they could do
也该把您的名字从犯人档案里除掉
is stop having you listed as an ex-convict
我觉得 这真是太不公了
which I think is, again, so unfair.
晚安 本杰明
Good night, Benjamin.
晚安 黛西
Good night, Daisy.
和预想的一样 我看着她离开
And as I knew I would, I watched her go.
后面他就没写了
That's the last thing he wrote.
你父亲死后的某一天
Sometime after your father passed,
我接到一个电话
there was a call.
喂
Hello.
是我 请讲
Yes, speaking.
抱歉 我不太明白
I'm sorry, I don't understand.
在路边那房子停下
It's the corner house.
请进
Come on in.
- 我是黛西・富勒 - 我叫大卫・埃尔南德斯
- I'm Daisy Fuller. - I'm David Hernandez,
是儿童福利中心奥尔良分局的
with the Orleans Parish Department of Child Welfare Services.
他住在一栋危楼里
He was living in a condemned building.
警方发现了这个
The police found this with him.
里面有这个地址 而且很多次提到你的名字
This address. It's got your name in it a lot.
他不太健康 已经去过医院了
He's in very poor health. He was taken to the hospital.
他似乎都分不清 自己是谁 在哪 好像是糊涂了
He doesn't seem to know who or where he is. He's very confused.
我告诉埃尔南德斯先生了 本杰明和我们一样
I was telling Mr. Hernandez that Benjamin is one of us.
要是他需要个住的地方 就呆在这吧
If he needs a place to stay, it's all right, he can stay here.
本杰明？
Benjamin?
你弹得真好听
You play beautifully.
他好像不太喜欢被人碰
He doesn't seem to like to be touched.
他记性时好时坏 不太能认人
He goes in and out of states of recognition.
医生说 他们也无能为力
The doctors say, if they didn't know any better,
他已经出现痴呆的症状了
he has the beginnings of dementia.
你还记得我吗？
Do you remember me?
我是黛西
I'm Daisy.
我叫本杰明
I'm Benjamin.
很高兴认识你 本杰明
It's nice to meet you, Benjamin.
你不介意我坐你旁边吧？ 我很喜欢听你弹琴
Would you mind if I sit with you? I would love to hear you play.
我认识你吗？
Do I know you?
- 我要吃早饭 - 此后 每天
- I want some breakfast. - And every day,
我都要过去看看 他过得怎么样
I would stop by to make sure that he was comfortable.
- 不 我没吃过 - 你刚刚吃完了
- No, I didn't. - You just finished eating.
别以为我不知道你们想耍我！
Don't think I don't know what you're doing!
你们这群该死的骗子！
You're all fucking liars!
他不信自己刚吃了早饭
He doesn't believe he just had his breakfast.
哦 咱来想想
Now, why don't we see
给你找点别的事做吧
if we can't find something else for you to do?
我总觉得 自己好像 有很多事情记不得了
I have a feeling there's a lot of things I can't remember.
比如呢？
Well, like what, sugar?
好像我已经活了很久
It's like there's this whole life I had,
却不记得过去的生活
and I can't remember what it was.
没事的
It's okay.
即使忘了 也没事的
It's okay to forget things.
很多时候 他根本不记得 自己是谁 自己在哪
Many times, he would simply forget who or where he was.
他在那 屋顶上
There he is, he's up there on the roof.
照顾他并不容易
It wasn't easy.
- 本杰明！ - 我看见了！
- Benjamin! - I can see everything!
- 我能看见大河！ - 没错
- I can see the big river! - That's right,
你当然什么都看得见 小可爱
you can see everything, sweetheart.
我看得见葬着妈妈的墓地
I can see the graveyard where Mama's buried,
- 那里还埋着很多其他人 - 快下来！
- and all those other people. - I want you to come down!
- 我要是会飞呢？ - 我认识个人就会飞
- What if I could fly? - I knew a man who could fly.
你下来 我就讲他的故事给你听
You come down and I'll tell you all about him.
谁快上去接他
Somebody go up there.
我搬进去住的时候 他相当于五岁
He was five when I moved in.
差不多就是我认识他时候那么大
Nearly the same age I was when I had met him.
“画里画的是大袋鼠
"This is the picture of Old Man Kangaroo
下午五点 他终于会蹦蹦跳了
"at 5:00 in the afternoon
他的双腿又粗又壮又漂亮”
"when he had got his beautiful hind legs."
岁月就这样流逝
The days passed.
我看着他 不会再走路
And I watched as he forgot how to walk
- 不会再说话 - 我叫什么呀
- and how to talk. - What's my name?
我叫黛西
I'm Daisy.
你会说“黛西”吗？
Can you say "Daisy"?
2002年 火车站换了新钟
In 2002, they put up a new clock in that train station.
2003年 春天
And in the spring of 2003,
他看着我
he looked at me
那一刻 我知道他认出我来了
and I knew that he knew who I was.
接着 他闭上了眼睛 好像是睡着了
And then he closed his eyes as if to go to sleep.
- 我真希望我认识他 - 现在你就认识了
- I wish I'd known him. - Now you do.
妈 我去看看怎么回事
Mom, I think I should go see what's going on.
晚安 本杰明
Good night, Benjamin.
有些人 生来 就注定可以悠闲地坐在河边
Some people are born to sit by a river.
有些人 会被闪电击中
Some get struck by lightning.
有些人 会音乐
Some have an ear for music.
有些人 是艺术家
Some are artists.
有些人 是游泳健将
Some swim.
有些人 懂纽扣
Some know buttons.
有些人 懂莎士比亚
Some know Shakespeare.
有些人 是妈妈
Some are mothers.
有些人 是舞者
And some people dance.